{"topic":"extra","questions":[{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Halloween is when lovers exchange cards and\r\ngifts.","Halloween has its roots in an ancient pagan festival marking the beginning of winter."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Halloween is an ancient festival and has its roots in the pagan festival to mark the beginning of winter."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Proms is an eight-week summer season of classical orchestral music.","The Proms is a series of tennis matches held every June in London."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Proms is an eight-week summer season of orchestral classical music that takes place in various venues, including the Royal Albert Hall in London."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nSome people rent land called 'an allotment', where they grow fruit and vegetables.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"A lot of people have gardens at home and will spend their free\r\ntime looking after them. Some people rent additional land called \u2018an allotment\u2019, where they grow fruit and vegetables."},{"question":"Who appoints life peers in the House of Lords?","choices":["The monarch","The Archbishop of Canterbury","The Speaker of the House of Commons","The Chief Whip"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Life peers are appointed by the monarch on the advice of the Prime Minister."},{"question":"In which battle during the First World War did the British suffer 60,000 casualties on the first day?","choices":["Agincourt","El Alamein","The Somme","Waterloo"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In July 1916 the British suffered 60,000 casualties on the first day of the Battle of the Somme."},{"question":"Who opens the new parliamentary session each year?","choices":["The Archbishop of Canterbury","The Prime Minister","The Speaker of the House of Commons","The King"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The King has important ceremonial roles, such as the opening of the new parliamentary session each year."},{"question":"Which TWO are famous British authors?","choices":["Mary Quant and Henry Moore","Thomas Hardy and Graham Greene","Thomas Hardy and Henry Moore","Graham Greene and Henry Moore"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Thomas Hardy's best-known novels include Far from the Madding Crowd and Jude the Obscure. Graham Greene's novels include The Heart of the Matter, The Honorary Consul, Brighton Rock and Our Man in Havana."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Charles, king of Scotland, was crowned King Charles II of England in 1660.","Bonnie Prince Charlie became King Charles II of England in 1660."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Scots declared Charles II to be king. He was crowned king of Scotland and led a Scottish army into England. After defeat at the Battles of Dunbar and Worcester, he fled to Europe. In May 1660, Parliament invited him to come back from exile in\r\nthe Netherlands. He was crowned King Charles II of England, Wales,\r\nScotland and Ireland."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nAnybody can be asked to serve on a jury, no matter how old they are.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Anyone who is on the electoral register and is aged 18\u201370 (18\u201375 in England and Wales) can be asked to serve on a jury."},{"question":"Which TWO of these figures were great Scottish thinkers of the Enlightenment?","choices":["Robert Louis Stevenson and David Hume","Adam Smith and David Hume","Robert Burns and Robert Louis Stevenson","Robert Burns and David Hume"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Many of the great thinkers of the Enlightenment were Scottish. Adam Smith developed ideas about economics. David Hume wrote about human nature."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\n'The Restoration' refers to the re-establishment of Catholicism as the official Church in the 17th century.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"In May 1660, Parliament invited Charles II to come back from exile in the Netherlands. He was crowned King Charles II of England, Wales,\r\nScotland and Ireland. This is referred to as 'The Restoration'."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThomas Hardy was a famous author who wrote Far from the Madding Crowd.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Thomas Hardy (1840\u20131928) was an author and poet. His best-known novels focus on rural society and include Far from the Madding Crowd and Jude the Obscure."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Chancellor of the Exchequer is responsible for crime, policing and immigration.","The Chancellor of the Exchequer is responsible for the economy."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Chancellor of the Exchequer is the cabinet minister responsible for the economy."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nBritain has never been at war with France.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Britain fought a number of wars with France during the Middle Ages and later."},{"question":"Which area of government policy is the responsibility of the Chancellor of the Exchequer?","choices":["Education","Health","Economy","Legal affairs"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Chancellor of the Exchequer is responsible for the economy, and is a member of the cabinet."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Magistrates usually work unpaid and do not need legal qualifications.","Magistrates must be specially trained legal experts who have been solicitors for three years."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Magistrates are members of the local community. They usually work unpaid and do not need legal qualifications."},{"question":"What was the Beveridge Report of 1942 about?","choices":["How to end the war in Europe","How to treat the Germans and Japanese after the war","Establishing a welfare state","The coalition government"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Beveridge Report of 1942, called Social Insurance and Allied Services, recommended that the government should find ways of fighting the five 'Giant Evils' of Want, Disease, Ignorance, Squalor and Idleness and provided the basis of the modern welfare state."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Speaker of the House of Commons remains a Member of Parliament (MP) after election as Speaker.","The Speaker of the House of Commons has to give up being an MP when elected as Speaker."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Speaker is neutral and does not represent a political party, but he or she remains an MP, represents a constituency and deals with constituents\u2019 problems like any other MP."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe Wimbledon Championships are associated with motor sports.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Wimbledon Championships is the oldest tennis tournament in the world."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are famous British authors?","choices":["Gustav Holst and J K Rowling","Sir Steve Redgrave and Sir Arthur Conan Doyle","Sir Steve Redgrave and Gustav Holst","Sir Arthur Conan Doyle and J K Rowling"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Sir Arthur Conan Doyle was a Scottish doctor and writer. He was best known for his stories about Sherlock Holmes, who was one of the first fictional detectives. J K Rowling wrote the Harry Potter series of children\u2019s books, which have enjoyed huge international success. She now writes fiction for adults as well."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nAll young people are sent a National Insurance number just before their 16th birthday.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"All young people in the UK are sent a National Insurance number just before their 16th birthday. It makes sure that the National Insurance Contributions and tax you pay are properly recorded against your name."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["There is no place in British society for extremism or intolerance.","Britain encourages people to have extreme views and to act upon them."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"British society is founded on fundamental values and principles which all those living in the UK should respect and support. There is no place for extremism or intolerance."},{"question":"Which TWO events are Christian festivals?","choices":["Easter and Bonfire Night","Boxing Day and Bonfire Night","Easter and Christmas Day","Christmas Day and Bonfire Night"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Easter and Christmas are two Christian festivals. Christmas celebrates the birth of Jesus Christ, and Easter marks his death on Good Friday and his rising from the dead on Easter Sunday."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["'The Divine Right of Kings' was the idea that the English king should rule France.","'The Divine Right of Kings' was the idea that the king was directly appointed by God to rule."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The 'Divine Right of Kings' was the idea that the king was directly appointed by God to rule."},{"question":"Which TWO chambers form the UK Parliament?","choices":["House of Lords and House of Representatives","House of Fraser and House of Commons","House of Commons and House of Representatives","House of Lords and House of Commons"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The UK Parliament is formed by the House of Commons and the House of Lords."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following do pressure and lobby groups do?","choices":["Organise violent protests and try to influence government policy","Assist MPs in their constituency work and represent the views of British business","Try to influence government policy and represent the views of British businesses","Organise violent protests and assist MPs in their constituency work"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Pressure and lobby groups are organisations which try to influence government policy. Some represent the views of British business. Others campaign on particular topics, such as the environment."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe Union Flag consists of four crosses, one for each part of the United Kingdom.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Union Flag consists of three crosses \u2013 the crosses of St George (England), St Andrew (Scotland) and St Patrick (Ireland)."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["After the age of 70, drivers must renew their licence every three years.","After the age of 70, drivers must renew their licence every five years."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Drivers can use their driving licence until they are 70 years old. After that, the licence is valid for three years at a time."},{"question":"Which TWO members of a family have a special day dedicated to them?","choices":["Uncles and aunts","Mothers and aunts","Fathers and aunts","Fathers and mothers"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"In the UK, Mothering Sunday is celebrated on the Sunday three weeks before Easter and Father's Day on the third Sunday in June. Children send cards and give gifts on these days."},{"question":"When did the Battle of Hastings take place?","choices":["1066","1415","1642","1940"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Battle of Hastings took place in 1066."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are responsibilities of Members of Parliament (MPs)?","choices":["Representing everyone in their constituency and supporting the government on all decisions and laws","Scrutinising and commenting on what the government is doing and representing only those who voted for them","Scrutinising and commenting on what the government is doing and supporting the government on all decisions and laws","Representing everyone in their constituency and scrutinising and commenting on what the government is doing"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"MPs have a number of different responsibilities, including representing everyone in their constituency, and scrutinising and commenting on what the government is doing."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIn 1588 the English defeated the Spanish Armada.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In 1588, the English defeated the Spanish Armada (a large fleet of ships), which had been sent by Spain to conquer England and restore Catholicism."},{"question":"Who first built the Tower of London?","choices":["Oliver Cromwell","Queen Elizabeth II","William the Conqueror","Winston Churchill"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Tower of London was first built by William the Conqueror\r\nafter he became king in 1066."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Roman army left England after 100 years to defend other parts of their Empire.","The Roman army left England after 400 years to defend other parts of their Empire."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Romans left England in AD 410 to defend other parts of their Empire. They had remained in Britain for 400 years."},{"question":"Which TWO are famous British fashion designers?","choices":["Capability Brown and Sir Edwin Lutyens","Mary Quant and Capability Brown","Mary Quant and Vivienne Westwood","Capability Brown and Vivienne Westwood"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Britain has produced many great designers. Leading fashion designers of recent years include Mary Quant, Alexander McQueen and Vivienne Westwood."},{"question":"In 1776, 13 British colonies declared their independence. In which part of the world were these colonies?","choices":["Australia","Canada","America","South Africa"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In 1776, 13 American colonies declared their independence,\r\nstating that people had a right to establish their own governments.\r\nThe colonists eventually defeated the British army and Britain\r\nrecognised the colonies\u2019 independence in 1783."},{"question":"Which language was spoken by people during the Iron Age?","choices":["Latin","A language that was part of the Celtic family","English","Anglo-Saxon"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The language Iron Age people spoke was part of the Celtic language family."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are examples of criminal law?","choices":["Disputes about faulty goods and discrimination in the workplace","Racial crime and discrimination in the workplace","Racial crime and disputes about faulty goods","Racial crime and selling tobacco to anyone under the age of 18"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Criminal law relates to crimes, which are usually investigated by the police or another authority such as a council, and which are punished by the courts. Examples of crimes include racial crime and selling tobacco to anyone under the age of 18."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The official name of the UK is the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland.","The official name of the UK is Great Britain."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The official name of the UK is the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland."},{"question":"Which TWO people are famous UK sports stars?","choices":["Sir Chris Hoy and Dame Kelly Holmes","Lucien Freud and Jane Austen","Dame Kelly Holmes and Jane Austen","Sir Chris Hoy and Lucien Freud"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Sir Chris Hoy is a Scottish cyclist who has won six gold and one silver Olympic medals. Dame Kelly Holmes won two gold medals for running in the 2004 Olympic Games."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Battle of Britain in 1940 was fought at sea.","The Battle of Britain in 1940 was fought in the air."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Battle of Britain was fought in the air above Britain in 1940. The British resisted with their fighter\r\nplanes and eventually won the crucial aerial battle against the\r\nGermans, in the summer of 1940."},{"question":"The Enlightenment led to major developments in which TWO areas?","choices":["Science and politics","History and theatre","Science and theatre","Politics and history"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"During the 18th century, new ideas about politics, science and philosophy developed. This is often called \u2018the Enlightenment'."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nParticipating in your community is a fundamental principle of British life.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"British society is founded on fundamental values and principles which all those living in the UK should respect and support. This includes participating in community life."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["To apply to become a permanent resident or naturalised citizen of the UK, you must have a UK bank account.","To apply to become a permanent resident or naturalised citizen of the UK, you must be able to speak and read English."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"To apply to become a permanent resident or naturalised citizen of the UK, you must be able to speak and read English. You must also have a good understanding of life in the UK."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The King is ceremonial head of the Commonwealth.","The King is ceremonial head of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO)."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The King is the ceremonial head of the Commonwealth, which currently has 54 member states."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The first professional UK football clubs were formed in the late 19th century","The first professional UK football clubs were formed in 1066."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Football has a long history in the UK and the first professional football clubs were formed in the late 19th century."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nEmmeline Pankhurst is famous for her role in the campaign to give women the vote in parliamentary elections in the UK.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Emmeline Pankhurst (1858\u20131928) helped found the Women\u2019s Social and Political Union (WSPU). This was the first group whose members were called \u2018suffragettes\u2019. The group used civil disobedience as part of their protest to gain the vote for women."},{"question":"Which TWO values are upheld by the Commonwealth association of countries?","choices":["Democracy and rule of law","Violence and rule of law","Democracy and communism","Communism and rule of law"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Commonwealth is based on the core values of democracy, good government and the rule of law."},{"question":"What is the aim of the United Nations?","choices":["To create a single free trade market","To prevent war and promote international peace and security","To examine decisions made by the European Union","To promote dictatorship"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The UK is part of the United Nations (UN), an international organisation with more than 190 countries as members. The UN was set up after the Second World War and aims to prevent war and promote international peace and security."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Industrial Revolution is the name given to the rapid development of industry in Britain in the 20th century.","The Industrial Revolution is the name given to the rapid development of industry that began in the 18th century."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Industrial Revolution refers to the rapid development of industry in Britain from the mid-18th century."},{"question":"For approximately how many years did the Romans remain in Britain?","choices":["50 years","100 years","400 years","600 years"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Romans remained in Britain for almost 400 years, from AD 43 to AD 410."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nHereditary peers have the automatic right to attend the House of Lords.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Since 1999, hereditary peers have lost the automatic right to attend the House of Lords. They now elect a few of their number to represent them."},{"question":"Which is the most popular sport in the UK?","choices":["Football","Rugby","Golf","Tennis"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Football is the UK's most popular sport. It has a long history in the UK and the first professional football clubs were formed in the late 19th century."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nMost people in the UK live in towns and cities.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Most people live in towns and cities but much of Britain is\r\nstill countryside."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following countries are members of the Commonwealth?","choices":["USA and Australia","Australia and Canada","Canada and Russia","Australia and Russia"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Australia and Canada are members of the Commonwealth. The King is the ceremonial head of the Commonwealth, which currently has 54 member states."},{"question":"On which date is St Patrick's Day celebrated?","choices":["1 March","17 March","23 April","30 November"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"St Patrick, the patron saint of Northern Ireland (and Ireland), has a special day on 17 March."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?                                                                                                     All people in the UK are expected to help the police prevent and detect crimes whenever they can.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"All people in the UK are expected to help the police prevent and detect crimes whenever they can."},{"question":"Which TWO responsibilities do you have as a resident of the UK?","choices":["Respect and obey the law, and take in and look after wild animals","Treat others with fairness and vote for the government in power","Treat others with fairness, and take in and look after wild animals","Respect and obey the law and treat others with fairness"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"There are responsibilities and freedoms which are shared by all those living in the UK. These include respecting and obeying the law, and treating others with fairness."},{"question":"Who do some local councils appoint as a ceremonial leader?","choices":["A local business leader","A member of the Royal Family","A local celebrity","A mayor"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Many local authorities appoint a mayor, who is the ceremonial leader of the council. (In some towns, a mayor is elected to be the effective leader of the administration.)"},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nHenry VIII is famous for marrying six times and breaking away from the Church of Rome.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Henry VIII had six wives and broke away from the Roman Catholic Church when the Pope refused to grant him a divorce so he could marry again."},{"question":"Which TWO issues can the devolved administrations pass laws on?","choices":["Health and foreign affairs","Health and education","Education and immigration","Foreign affairs and immigration"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The devolved administrations in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland can pass laws on matters that directly affect them, including health and education."},{"question":"By joining a political party, what TWO activities might you be involved in?","choices":["Violent clashes with other political parties, and handing out leaflets in the street","Joining your MPs for sessions in the House of Commons, and handing out leaflets in the street","Handing out leaflets in the street, and knocking on people's doors asking for support","Joining your MP for sessions in the House of Commons, and knocking on people's doors and asking for support"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Political parties welcome new members. Members work hard to persuade people to vote for their candidates \u2013 for instance, by handing out leaflets in the street or by knocking on people's doors and asking for their support. This is called 'canvassing'."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIn the UK, there are now a record number of people aged 85 and over.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"People in the UK are living longer than ever before. There are now a record number of people aged 85 and over."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Wales and Northern Ireland each have their own Church of state.","There is no established Church in Wales or Northern Ireland."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"There is no established Church in Wales or Northern Ireland."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nA public vote in 2002 decided that Winston Churchill was the greatest Briton of all time.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In 2002, Winston Churchill (1874\u20131965) was voted the greatest Briton of all time by the public."},{"question":"What system of government does the UK have?","choices":["Communist government","Dictatorship","Parliamentary democracy","Federal government"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The system of government in the UK is a parliamentary democracy. The UK is divided into parliamentary constituencies, and voters in each constituency elect a Member of Parliament (MP) to represent them."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The UK is governed by the parliament sitting in Westminster.","The UK is governed by the parliament sitting in Edinburgh."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The UK is governed by the parliament sitting in Westminster. Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland also have parliaments or assemblies of their own, with devolved powers in defined areas."},{"question":"Which TWO new national bodies began operating in 1999?","choices":["Welsh Assembly (now called the Senedd) and Scottish Parliament","Scottish Parliament and English Parliament","House of Lords and Welsh Assembly (now called the Senedd)","House of Lords and Scottish Parliament"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Since 1997, some powers have been devolved from the central government to give people in Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland more control over matters that directly affect them. There has been a Welsh Assembly (now called the Senedd) and a Scottish Parliament since 1999."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following were British inventions?","choices":["Television and the jet engine","The jet engine and radio","Television and the diesel engine","Radio and the diesel engine"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The television and jet engine are two of many important inventions by Britons in the 20th century."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIn 1833 the Emancipation Act abolished slavery throughout the British Empire.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In 1833 the Emancipation Act abolished slavery throughout the British Empire."},{"question":"What is the name of the Northern Ireland Assembly building?","choices":["The Houses of Parliament","The Senedd","Stormont","Holyrood House"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Northern Ireland Assembly building is known as Stormont."},{"question":"What happens when Members of Parliament (MPs) hold surgeries?","choices":["Local councillors meet their MP to discuss local issues","Members of the public meet their MP to discuss issues","MPs meet doctors to discuss local health issues","MPs meet the press to discuss national issues"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Many MPs hold regular local \u2018surgeries\u2019, where constituents can go in person to talk about issues that are of concern to them."},{"question":"Where did the Vikings come from?","choices":["Germany and Austria","Belgium and Holland","Denmark, Norway and Sweden","France and Luxembourg"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Vikings first raided Britain in AD 789. They came from Denmark, Norway and Sweden."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Sake Dean Mahomet is famous for introducing tea-drinking and bungalows to Britain from India.","Sake Dean Mahomet is famous for introducing curry houses to Britain from India."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Sake Dean Mahomet (1759\u20131851) opened the first curry house in Britain in 1810."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe Civil War between Charles I and Parliament in the mid-17th century led to Oliver Cromwell becoming king of England.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"At the end of the Civil War, England became a republic and Oliver Cromwell was given the title of Lord Protector."},{"question":"Where is the Welsh Parliament (the Senedd) based?","choices":["London","Newport","Glasgow","Cardiff"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The Welsh Parliament (the Senedd) is based in Cardiff, the capital city of Wales."},{"question":"What did St Augustine and St Columba do during the Anglo-Saxon period?","choices":["They invented new farming techniques.","They led an uprising in Wales.","They helped to spread Christianity across Britain.","They fought courageously against the Romans."],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"St Augustine and St Columba were early Christian missionaries who came to Britain to preach about Christianity. St Columba founded a monastery on the Isle of Iona. St Augustine spread Christianity in the south and became the first Archbishop of Canterbury."},{"question":"Which TWO of these novels are by Charles Dickens?","choices":["Harry Potter and Great Expectations","Great Expectations and Oliver Twist","Harry Potter, and Pride and Prejudice","Pride and Prejudice, and Oliver Twist"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Charles Dickens wrote a number of very famous novels, including Oliver Twist and Great Expectations."},{"question":"Which TWO are influential British bands?","choices":["The National Trust and The Rolling Stones","The National Trust and The Beatles","The Rolling Stones and The Beatles","The Rolling Stones and The Royal Family"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Beatles and The Rolling Stones are two influential British bands that continue to have an influence on music both in the UK and abroad."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Mary, Queen of Scots was unrelated to Queen Elizabeth I.","Mary, Queen of Scots was a cousin of Queen Elizabeth I."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Mary was Elizabeth I\u2019s cousin. She was eventually executed, accused of plotting against Elizabeth I."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The official home of the Prime Minister is 10 Downing Street.","The official home of the Prime Minister is Buckingham Palace."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The official home of the Prime Minister is 10 Downing Street, in central London, near the Houses of Parliament. He or she also has a country house outside London called Chequers."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following would you contact for help on a legal matter?","choices":["A solicitor and Citizens Advice","A solicitor and a local councillor","A local councillor and your local Member of Parliament (MP)","Citizens Advice and your local Member of Parliament (MP)"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Solicitors are trained lawyers who give advice on legal matters, take\r\naction for their clients and represent their clients in court. Citizens Advice can give you names of local solicitors and tell you which areas of law they specialise in."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE? British scientists were the first to clone a mammal successfully.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"True - the British team were the first to succeed in cloning a mammal, Dolly the sheep."},{"question":"Why is 1918 an important date in the history of women's rights?","choices":["The first divorce laws were introduced.","Women over the age of 30 were given voting rights.","Equal pay laws were passed.","Women were made legally responsible for their children."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"In 1918, women over the age of 30 were given voting rights. In 1928, women were given the right to vote at the age of 21, the same as men."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are Christian festivals celebrated in the UK?","choices":["Halloween and New Year","Easter and Christmas","Christmas and New Year","Easter and Halloween"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Easter and Christmas are two Christian festivals. Christmas celebrates the birth of Jesus Christ, and Easter marks his death on Good Friday and his rising from the dead on Easter Sunday."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nForcing another person to marry is a criminal offence in the UK.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Forced marriage is where one or both parties do not or cannot give their consent to enter into the partnership. This is a criminal offence in the UK."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["In the UK, pregnant women have the same right to work as anyone else.","In the UK, employers have the right not to employ pregnant women."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"UK laws ensure people are not treated unfairly in any area of life or work because of their age, disability, sex, pregnancy and maternity, race, religion or belief, sexuality or marital status."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Florence Nightingale is associated with policing.","Florence Nightingale is associated with nursing."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Florence Nightingale treated soldiers who were fighting in the Crimean War. She later established the Nightingale Training School for nurses at St Thomas' Hospital in London. She is often regarded as the founder of modern nursing."},{"question":"Which TWO patron saints' days occur in March?","choices":["St David and St George","St David and St Patrick","St David and St Andrew","St Patrick and St Andrew"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"St David, the patron saint of Wales, has a special day on 1 March. St Patrick, the patron saint of Northern Ireland (and Ireland), has a special day on 17 March."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are famous Paralympians?","choices":["Ellie Simmonds and Baroness Tanni Grey-Thompson","Ellie Simmonds and Dame Ellen MacArthur","Dame Jessica Ennis-Hill and Baroness Tanni Grey-Thompson","Dame Jessica Ennis-Hill and Dame Ellen MacArthur"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Ellie Simmonds won gold medals for swimming at the 2008, 2012 and 2016 Paralympic Games. Baroness Tanni Grey-Thompson is an athlete who uses a wheelchair and won 16 Paralympic medals."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIf an accused person is aged 18 to 21, their case will be heard in a Youth Court.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"If an accused person is aged 10 to 17, the case is normally held in a Youth Court."},{"question":"In 1348 a third of the populations of England, Wales and Scotland died as a result of which plague?","choices":["The Blue Death","The White Death","The Green Death","The Black Death"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"In 1348, a disease, probably a form of plague, came to Britain.\r\nThis was known as the Black Death. One third of the population of\r\nEngland died and a similar proportion in Scotland and Wales. This was one of the worst disasters ever to strike Britain."},{"question":"Which TWO are plays by William Shakespeare?","choices":["A Midsummer Night's Dream, and Oliver Twist","Romeo and Juliet, and Oliver Twist","A Midsummer Night's Dream, and Romeo and Juliet","Pride and Prejudice, and Romeo and Juliet"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Among the many plays that Shakespeare wrote are A Midsummer Night's Dream and Romeo and Juliet."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The official church of state in England is the Church of England.","There is no official church of state in England."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Church of England is the official church of state in England. The monarch is the head of the Church of England."},{"question":"Who invaded England in 1066?","choices":["Richard the Lionheart","King Canute","William, the Duke of Normandy","Harold of Wessex"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In 1066, William, the Duke of Normandy, invaded England and defeated King Harold at the Battle of Hastings."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE OR FALSE?\r\nThe National Citizen Service provides military training to young people.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The National Citizen Service gives 16- and 17-year-olds the opportunity to enjoy outdoor activities, develop their skills and take part in a community project."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["In 1776, 13 American colonies declared their independence from Britain.","The American colonists were eventually defeated by the British."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In 1776, 13 American colonies declared their independence from Britain, stating that people had a right to establish their own governments."},{"question":"Which TWO were 20th-century British discoveries or inventions?","choices":["Radium and the printing press","The hovercraft and radium","Penicillin and the printing press","The hovercraft and penicillin"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The hovercraft was invented by Sir Christopher Cockerell and penicillin was discovered by Sir Alexander Fleming."},{"question":"Which TWO families contested the Wars of the Roses in the 15th century?","choices":["The House of York and the House of Windsor","The House of Windsor and the House of Lancaster","The House of Tudor and the House of Windsor","The House of York and the House of Lancaster"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"A civil war known as the Wars of the Roses broke out in 1455 between supporters of the House of Lancaster and the House of York. It ended in 1485 at the Battle of Bosworth Field, when King Richard III of the House of York was killed."},{"question":"Which UK city hosted the 2012 Paralympic Games?","choices":["Belfast","Cardiff","Edinburgh","London"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The Paralympic Games for 2012 were hosted in London."},{"question":"Once you are aged 17, which TWO vehicles can you learn to drive?","choices":["Car and fire engine","Motor cycle and fire engine","Motor cycle and heavy goods vehicle","Motor cycle and car"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"In the UK, you must be at least 17 years old to drive a car or motor cycle and you must have a driving licence to drive on public roads."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Proceedings in Parliament cannot be reported in the press.","Proceedings in Parliament are broadcast on television."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Proceedings in Parliament are broadcast on television and published in official reports called Hansard. Most people get information about political issues and events from newspapers (often called \u2018the press\u2019), television, radio and the internet."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe Channel Islands have their own governments.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Channel Islands have their own governments and are called 'Crown dependencies'."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["There is a yearly sailing race on the River Thames between Oxford and Cambridge universities.","There is a yearly rowing race on the River Thames between Oxford and Cambridge universities."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Rowing is a popular sport in the UK, both as a leisure activity and as a competitive sport. There is a popular yearly race on the River Thames between Oxford and Cambridge universities."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are fundamental principles of British life?","choices":["Only driving your car on weekdays and participation in community life","Participation in community life and tolerance of those with different faiths and beliefs","Only driving your car on weekdays and growing your own fruit and vegetables","Growing your own fruit and vegetables and tolerance of those with different faiths and beliefs"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"British society is founded on fundamental values and principles which all those living in the UK should respect and support. These include participation in community life and tolerance of those with different faiths and beliefs."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Members of Parliament (MPs) are elected through a system called 'first past the post'.","MPs are elected through a system called 'proportional representation'."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"MPs are elected through a system called 'first past the post'. This means that in each constituency, the candidate who gets the most votes is elected."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are major horse-racing events in the UK?","choices":["The Open Championship and the Scottish Grand National","The Open Championship and the Six Nations Championship","Scottish Grand National and the Six Nations Championship","Scottish Grand National and Royal Ascot"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Famous horse-racing events include: Royal Ascot, a five-day race meeting in Berkshire attended by members of the Royal Family; and the Scottish Grand National at Ayr."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["A free press means that what is written in newspapers is free from government control.","A free press means that newspapers are given out free of charge."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The UK has a free press. This means that what is written in newspapers is free from government control."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe criminal court systems in England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland are identical.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"There are some differences between the criminal court systems in different parts of the UK."},{"question":"When walking your dog in a public place, what must you ensure?","choices":["That your dog wears a special dog coat","That your dog never strays more than 3 metres away from you","That your dog does not come into contact with other dogs","That your dog wears a collar showing the name and address of the owner"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"All dogs in public places must wear a collar showing the name and address of the owner."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Plymouth, Norwich and Leeds are cities in England.","Newport, Swansea and Cardiff are cities in Scotland."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Plymouth, Norwich and Leeds are cities in England."},{"question":"Which of these is a fundamental principle of British life?","choices":["Actively supporting your local football team","Participation in community life","Ignoring your neighbours","Eating fish on a Friday"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Participation in community life is one of the fundamental values and principles which all those living in the UK should respect and support."},{"question":"Why was the Habeas Corpus Act of 1679 so important?","choices":["It ensured no person could be held prisoner unlawfully.","It allowed people to bury the dead where they wished.","It ensured that those who died could only be buried by a relative.","It ended capital punishment in England."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Habeas Corpus Act was a very \r\nimportant piece of legislation which remains relevant today. Habeas corpus is Latin for \u2018you must present the person in court\u2019. The Act guaranteed that no one could be held prisoner unlawfully."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["In a Crown Court case, the judge decides the penalty when someone is found guilty.","In a Crown Court case, the jury decides the penalty when someone is found guilty."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"If the jury in a Crown Court case finds the defendant guilty, the judge decides on the penalty."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["People in paid work need to pay National Insurance Contributions.","People in paid work do not need to pay National Insurance Contributions."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Almost everybody in the UK who is in paid work must pay National Insurance Contributions. Employees have their National Insurance Contributions deducted from their pay by their employer."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIreland is part of the UK.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The UK is made up of England, Scotland, Wales and Northern\r\nIreland. The rest of Ireland is an independent country."},{"question":"Dunkirk is associated with which TWO events?","choices":["The fall of Singapore and small boats coming to the rescue","The D-Day landings and the fall of Singapore","The rescue of 300,000 men and small boats coming to the rescue","The fall of Singapore and the rescue of 300,000 men"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In 1940, many civilian volunteers in small pleasure and fishing boats from Britain helped the Navy to rescue 300,000 men from the beaches around Dunkirk. The evacuation gave rise to the phrase \u2018the Dunkirk spirit\u2019."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are Christian groups?","choices":["Roman Catholics and Baptists","Hindus and Baptists","Roman Catholics and Sikhs","Roman Catholics and Buddhists"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Roman Catholics and Baptists are Christian groups. Baptists are a Protestant Christian group. Other Protestant groups include the Church of England, Methodists, Presbyterians and Quakers."},{"question":"Dylan Thomas was a famous writer and poet from which country?","choices":["England","Scotland","Wales","Northern Ireland"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Dylan Thomas, who lived from 1914 until 1953, was a Welsh poet and writer. One of his most well-known works is Under Milk Wood."},{"question":"Which event is remembered on 5 November each year?","choices":["The end of the Second World War","The King's birthday","A plan to blow up the Houses of Parliament in 1605","The defeat of the Spanish Armada in 1588"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Bonfire Night, 5 November, is an occasion when people in Great Britain set off fireworks at home or in special displays. The origin of this celebration was an event in 1605, when a group of Catholics led by Guy Fawkes failed in their plan to kill the Protestant king with a bomb in the Houses of Parliament."},{"question":"Who were the 'suffragettes'?","choices":["Women who left the UK to live in America","Women who campaigned for women's votes","Women who left their jobs when they got married","Women who stayed at home to raise a family"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, an increasing number of women campaigned and demonstrated for women's rights, in particular the right to vote. They formed the women\u2019s suffrage movement and became known\r\nas \u2018suffragettes\u2019."},{"question":"Which of the following is a Stone Age monument in the UK?","choices":["Globe Theatre","Nelson's Column","Stonehenge","Windsor Castle"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Stonehenge is a Stone Age monument in the English county of Wiltshire. It was probably a special gathering place for seasonal ceremonies."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Civil servants are politically neutral.","Civil servants have to be politically aligned to the elected government."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Civil servants are chosen on merit\r\nand are politically neutral \u2013 they are not political appointees."},{"question":"For which TWO types of literature is William Shakespeare famous?","choices":["Plays and sonnets","Biographies and sonnets","Novels and biographies","Novels and plays"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"William Shakespeare was a famous playwright and sonnet writer."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Most shops in the UK open seven days a week.","All shops in the UK close on Sundays."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Most shops in the UK open seven days a week, although trading hours on Sundays and public holidays are generally reduced."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe jet engine and radar were developed in Britain in the 1830s.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The jet engine and the radar were both developed in Britain in the 1930s."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are linked to football?","choices":["The Premier League and The Open","UEFA and the Premier League","The Ashes and UEFA","The Ashes and The Open"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The English Premier League attracts a huge international\r\naudience. Many of the best players in the world play in the Premier League. Many UK teams also compete in competitions such as the UEFA (Union of European Football Associations) Champions League, against other teams from Europe."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following wars were English kings involved in during the Middle Ages?","choices":["The Crusades and the First World War","The Crimean War and the Crusades","The Crimean War and the Hundred Years War","The Crusades and the Hundred Years War"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"During the Middle Ages, the English kings fought a number\r\nof wars abroad. Many knights took part in the Crusades, in which\r\nEuropean Christians fought for control of the Holy Land. English\r\nkings also fought a long war with France, called the Hundred\r\nYears War (even though it actually lasted 116 years)."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe flower that is particularly associated with England is the rose.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The countries that make up the UK\r\nall have flowers which are particularly associated with them and which are sometimes worn on national saints\u2019 days. In England, the flower is the rose."},{"question":"Textile and engineering firms found workers from which TWO countries after the Second World War?","choices":["Canada and India","India and Pakistan","South Africa and Pakistan","South Africa and India"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Textile and engineering firms from the north of England and the Midlands sent agents to India and Pakistan to find workers."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe First World War ended at 11.00 am on 11 November 1918.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The First World War ended at 11.00 am on 11th November 1918 with victory for Britain and its allies."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIn the 1830s and 1840s a group called the Chartists campaigned for reform to the voting system.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Chartists campaigned for reform of the voting system. The changes they wanted included elections every year and for all regions to be equal in the electoral system."},{"question":"Which of the following is part of the UK?","choices":["The Channel Islands","Northern Ireland","The Isle of Man","The Falkland Islands"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Northern Ireland is part of the UK, along with England, Wales and Scotland."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nCharles Dickens was famous for writing musicals.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Charles Dickens wrote a number of famous novels, including Oliver Twist and Great Expectations."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["National parks are areas of protected countryside that everyone can visit.","National parks are national sports stadiums for people to hold sporting events."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"National parks are areas of protected countryside that everyone can visit, and where people live, work and look after the landscape. There are 15 national parks in England, Wales and Scotland."},{"question":"Which jubilee did Queen Elizabeth II celebrate in 2012?","choices":["Platinum Jubilee (70 years as Queen)","Diamond Jubilee (60 years as Queen)","Silver Jubilee (25 years as Queen)","Golden Jubilee (50 years as Queen)"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Queen Elizabeth II reigned from 1952 until her death in 2022. In 2012 she celebrated her Diamond Jubilee (60 years as Queen)."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The BBC is primarily funded by advertising.","The BBC is partially funded by the state."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The BBC is a British public service broadcaster providing television and radio programmes. Although it receives some state funding, it is independent of the government."},{"question":"Which TWO groups were associated with King Charles I and Parliament during the English Civil War?","choices":["Tories and Roundheads","Cavaliers and Luddites","Roundheads and Cavaliers","Roundheads and Luddites"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Supporters of the king were known as Cavaliers and supporters of Parliament were known as Roundheads."},{"question":"Which TWO are political parties in the UK?","choices":["Modern Party and Conservative Party","Office Party and Labour Party","Modern Party and Labour Party","Conservative Party and Labour Party"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The major political parties in the UK include the Conservative Party, the Labour Party and the Liberal Democrats."},{"question":"In which part of the British Empire did the Boer War of 1899\u20131902 take place?","choices":["India","Canada","Australia","South Africa"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The Boer War took place in South Africa between the British army and the Boer settlers, who originally came from the Netherlands."},{"question":"Which TWO are 20th-century British inventions?","choices":["The World Wide Web and the diesel engine","Television and the World Wide Web","Mobile phones and the diesel engine","Television and mobile phones"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Television was developed by John Logie Baird in the 1920s. Tim Berners-Lee invented the World Wide Web in 1990."},{"question":"Why was the Magna Carta important?","choices":["It gave all men the vote.","It restricted the power of the monarch.","It established a system of free education.","It gave women legal rights."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"King John was forced by his noblemen to agree to a number of demands. The result was a charter of rights called the Magna Carta, which restricted the king's power to collect taxes or to make or change laws."},{"question":"What task is associated with the National Trust?","choices":["Building new public roads","Preserving old aircraft","Preserving important buildings and places","Managing investment accounts"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Many parts of the countryside and places of interest are kept open\r\nby the National Trust in England, Wales and Northern Ireland and\r\nthe National Trust for Scotland. Both are charities that work to\r\npreserve important buildings, coastline and countryside in the\r\nUK."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?                                                                               'We shall fight on the beaches' is a famous quote from a speech by Queen Elizabeth I about the Spanish Armada.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"'We shall fight on the beaches' is a quote from a speech by Winston Churchill, the Prime Minister,  after the evacuation of Dunkirk in 1940."},{"question":"In everyday language, people may say 'rain stopped play'. With which sport is this phrase associated?","choices":["Football","Cricket","Rugby league","Horse racing"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The expression 'rain stopped play' is associated with cricket. The phrase has now passed into everyday usage."},{"question":"Which TWO are famous horse-racing events?","choices":["The Cup Final and the Six Nations","The Grand National and Royal Ascot","Royal Ascot and the Six Nations","The Grand National and the Cup Final"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Famous horse-racing events include: Royal Ascot, a five-day race meeting in Berkshire attended by members of the Royal Family; the Grand National at Aintree near Liverpool; and the Scottish Grand National at Ayr."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are famous British artists?","choices":["David Hockney and Henry Moore","David Hockney and Sir Edward Elgar","Sir Edward Elgar and Henry Moore","Sir Andy Murray and Sir Edward Elgar"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"David Hockney was an important contributor to the 'pop art' movement of the 1960s. Henry Moore is best known for his large bronze abstract sculptures."},{"question":"Which queen is remembered for fighting against the Romans?","choices":["Elizabeth","Boudicca","Victoria","Anne"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"One of the tribal leaders who fought against the Romans was Boudicca, the queen of the Iceni in what is now eastern England. She is still remembered today and there is\r\na statue of her on Westminster Bridge in London, near the Houses\r\nof Parliament."},{"question":"What is a jury made up of?","choices":["People working in high-powered jobs","People randomly chosen from the electoral register","People who are members of political parties","People who have submitted an application form and been accepted"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"A jury is made up of members of the public chosen at random from the local electoral register."},{"question":"Who elects Police and Crime Commissioners (PCCs)?","choices":["The police","The Home Office","The public","Members of Parliament"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The public elects Police and Crime Commissioners (PCCs) in England and Wales. PCCs are responsible for the delivery of an efficient and effective police force."},{"question":"Which group of refugees settled in England between 1680 and 1720?","choices":["Welsh","Germans","Bretons","Huguenots"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Between 1680 and 1720 many refugees called Huguenots came from France. They were Protestants and had been persecuted for their religion."},{"question":"Which significant change was introduced by the Education Act of 1944?","choices":["New public examinations","Free secondary education in England and Wales","Primary education for all","The requirement to wear school uniform"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Education Act of 1944 (also called 'The Butler Act' after the Minister of Education at the time, R A Butler) introduced free secondary education in England and Wales."},{"question":"Which festival is celebrated on 31 October?","choices":["Valentine's Day","Bonfire Night","Halloween","Hogmanay"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Halloween is celebrated on 31 October."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nSnowdonia is a national park in Northern Ireland.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Snowdonia is a national park in North Wales. Its most well-known landmark is Snowdon, which is the highest mountain in Wales."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nPeople are able to buy National Lottery tickets in the UK if they are aged 14 or over.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"People under 18 are not allowed to participate in the National Lottery."},{"question":"Which court would you use to get back money that was owed to you?","choices":["County Court","Magistrates' Court","Youth Court","Coroner's Court"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"County Courts deal with a wide range of civil disputes. These\r\ninclude people trying to get back money that is owed to them."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nBefore 1215 there were few formal limits to the power of the king of England.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"There were few formal limits to the king\u2019s power until 1215. In that year, King John was forced by his noblemen to agree to a number of demands. The result was a charter of rights called the Magna Carta\r\n(which means the Great Charter). The Magna Carta established the\r\nidea that even the king was subject to the law."},{"question":"Why was Henry VIII an important English monarch?","choices":["He broke from the Church of Rome.","He established the RAF.","He invaded Sweden.","He re-established the Catholic Church in England."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Henry VIII broke from the Catholic Church of Rome when the Pope refused to let him divorce his first wife. Henry established the Church of England. In this new Church, the king, not the Pope, had the power to appoint bishops and order how people should worship."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nMargaret Thatcher was the longest-serving UK Prime Minister of the 20th century.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Margaret Thatcher was the longest-serving Prime Minister of the 20th century. She won her first General Election in 1979 and was re-elected in 1983 and 1987. She left office in 1990."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following issues can the Northern Ireland Assembly make decisions on?","choices":["Defence and foreign affairs","Agriculture and social services","Defence and agriculture","Foreign affairs and social services"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Northern Ireland Assembly can make decisions on various issues, including agriculture and social services."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nCardiff, Swansea and Newport are cities in England.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Cardiff, Swansea and Newport are all cities in Wales."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nKing Henry VIII established the Church of England when the Pope refused to grant him a divorce.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"To divorce his first wife (Catherine of Aragon), Henry needed the approval of the Pope. When the Pope refused, Henry established the Church of England. In this new Church, the king, not the Pope, would have the power to appoint bishops and order how people should worship."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nSt Helena is a Crown dependency.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"St Helena is a British overseas territory and not a Crown dependency."},{"question":"How old must you be to ride a moped in the UK?","choices":["18","25","16","21"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In the UK you need to be at least 16 years old to ride a moped."},{"question":"What important change to our voting rights took place in 1969?","choices":["Women over 35 were given the vote.","Prisoners were given the vote.","The voting age was reduced to 18 for men and women.","Compulsory voting was introduced."],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In 1969, the voting age was reduced to 18 for men and women."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nShakespeare was a playwright and actor.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Shakespeare was born in\r\nStratford-upon-Avon, England. He\r\nwas a playwright and actor and\r\nwrote many poems and plays."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Anglo-Saxon kingdoms in England united under King Alfred the Great.","The Anglo-Saxon kingdoms in England united under King Kenneth MacAlpin."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Anglo-Saxon kingdoms in England united under King Alfred the Great, who defeated the Vikings."},{"question":"What is the role of a jury at a court trial?","choices":["To decide whether evidence should be allowed to be heard","To decide the sentence that the accused should be given","To decide who the judge should be","To decide a verdict based on what they have heard."],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"A jury has to listen to the evidence presented at the trial and then decide a verdict of \u2018guilty\u2019 or \u2018not guilty\u2019 based on what they have heard. In Scotland, a third verdict of \u2018not proven\u2019 is also possible. If the jury finds a defendant guilty, the judge decides on the penalty."},{"question":"Which cross on the Union Flag represents the patron saint of England?","choices":["The diagonal white cross","The diagonal red cross","The upright red cross","None of these"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The cross of St George, patron saint of England, is an upright red cross on a white ground."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Reform Act of 1832 greatly increased the number of people who had the right to vote.","The Reform Act of 1832 increased the power of the House of Lords."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Reform Act of 1832 greatly increased the number of people with the right to vote. The Act also abolished the old pocket and rotten boroughs (parliamentary seats where there were few voters) and more parliamentary seats were given to the towns and cities."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["A famous sailing event is held at Cowes on the Isle of Wight.","A famous sailing event is held in the city of Norwich."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Many sailing events are held throughout the UK, the most famous of which is at Cowes on the Isle of Wight."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["When you apply to become a UK citizen or permanent resident, you can choose which laws and responsibilities you want to accept.","When you apply to become a UK citizen or permanent resident, you will be agreeing to respect the laws, values and traditions of the UK."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Applying to become a permanent resident or citizen of the UK is an important decision and commitment. You will be agreeing to accept the responsibilities which go with permanent residence and to respect the laws, values and traditions of the UK."},{"question":"What is one of the roles of school governors?","choices":["Setting the strategic direction of the school","Marking students' homework","Giving teachers ideas for lesson plans","Serving food and drink in the canteen"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"School governors have an important part to play in raising school standards. This includes setting the strategic direction of the school."},{"question":"What must you do in order to vote in elections?","choices":["Pay income tax in the year before the election","Put your name on the electoral register","Register your identity with the police","Pass an electoral test"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"To be able to vote in a parliamentary or local election, you must have your name on the electoral register. You can register by contacting your local council electoral registration office."},{"question":"What happened to Margaret Thatcher in 1979 to make her famous in UK history?","choices":["She took part in the Olympics.","She became a High Court judge.","She became the first woman Prime Minister.","She was made a general in the British army."],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Following the Conservative victory in the General Election in\r\n1979, Margaret Thatcher became the first woman Prime Minister\r\nof the UK. She was the longest-serving Prime Minister of the\r\n20th century, remaining in office until 1990."},{"question":"At what age can you vote in a General Election in the UK?","choices":["16","18","21","23"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The present voting age of 18 was set in 1969."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Baptists, Methodists and Quakers are denominations of the Roman Catholic Church.","Baptists, Methodists, and Quakers are Protestant Christian groups."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Baptists, Methodists and Quakers are Protestant Christian groups."},{"question":"Which TWO are famous UK landmarks?","choices":["Snowdonia and Notre Dame","Loch Lomond and Notre Dame","Snowdonia and Loch Lomond","Grand Canyon and Loch Lomond"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Snowdonia is a national park in North Wales. Loch Lomond is the largest expanse of fresh water in mainland Britain and probably the best-known part of the Trossachs National Park."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following is William Shakespeare famous for writing?","choices":["Plays and TV dramas","Poems and radio scripts","Plays and poems","TV dramas and radio scripts"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"William Shakespeare (1564\u20131616) was a playwright and actor. His plays and poems are still performed and studied\r\nin Britain and other countries today."},{"question":"During the 'Great Depression' of the 1930s, which TWO major new industries developed?","choices":["Automobiles and aviation","Ship building and coal mining","Ship building and aviation","Coal mining and automobiles"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"During the Great Depression of the 1930s, many traditional heavy industries, such as shipbuilding, went into decline. However, new industries - such as aviation and the automobile industry - developed."},{"question":"What are Beowulf, The Tyger and She Walks in Beauty?","choices":["Plays","Films","Poems","Novels"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Beowulf is an Anglo-Saxon poem, The Tyger is a poem by William Blake, and She Walks in Beauty is a poem by Lord Byron."},{"question":"Which of the following is a traditional pub game in the UK?","choices":["Scrabble","Pool","Rounders","Poker"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Pool and darts are traditional pub games. Pub quizzes are also popular."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are traditional British foods?","choices":["Strudel and haggis","Welsh cakes and haggis","Sushi and Welsh cakes","Sushi and haggis"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Welsh cakes are a traditional Welsh snack made from flour, dried fruits and spices. Haggis, a traditional Scottish food, is a sheep's stomach stuffed with offal, suet, onions and oatmeal."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The capital city of Northern Ireland is Swansea.","The capital city of Northern Ireland is Belfast."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The capital city of Northern Ireland is Belfast."},{"question":"Which of the following is a traditional food associated with Scotland?","choices":["Roast beef","Ulster fry","Fish and chips","Haggis"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Haggis is a traditional Scottish food. It is a sheep\u2019s stomach stuffed with offal, suet, onions and oatmeal."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Industrial Revolution was the rapid development of industry in the 18th and 19th centuries.","The Industrial Revolution introduced changes in the banking system in the 1970s."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Industrial Revolution was the rapid development of industry in Britain in the 18th and 19th centuries. The development of machinery and use of steam power transformed industries such as manufacturing and mining."},{"question":"What do Sir William Golding, Seamus Heaney and Harold Pinter have in common?","choices":["They were all famous British athletes.","They all became Prime Minister.","They were part of the first British expedition to the North Pole.","They have all won the Nobel Prize in Literature."],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Several British writers, including the novelist Sir William Golding, the poet Seamus Heaney, and the playwright Harold Pinter, have won the Nobel Prize in Literature."},{"question":"When is Boxing Day?","choices":["The day after Easter","The day after Christmas Day","The last Monday in August","The first day in May"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Boxing Day is the day after Christmas Day and is a public holiday."},{"question":"In the 19th century, the UK produced more than half the world's supply of one of these products. Which one?","choices":["Cotton cloth","Beer","Cigarettes","Rubber"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In the 19th century the UK produced more than half of the world's supplies of iron, coal and cotton cloth."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Big Ben is a mountain in eastern England","Big Ben is the nickname for the great bell of the clock at the Houses of Parliament."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Big Ben is the nickname for the great bell of the clock at the Houses of Parliament in London. Many people call the clock Big\r\nBen as well."},{"question":"Which Scottish king defeated the English at the Battle of Bannockburn in 1314?","choices":["William Wallace","Robert the Bruce","Malcolm","Andrew"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The English were defeated at the Battle of Bannockburn by Robert the Bruce in 1314."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The civil service largely consists of political appointees.","The civil service is politically neutral."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Civil servants support the government in developing and\r\nimplementing its policies. They are chosen on merit and are politically neutral \u2013 they are not political appointees."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIn 1707 the kingdoms of England and Scotland were united.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Act of Union, known as the\r\nTreaty of Union in Scotland, was agreed in 1707 and created\r\nthe Kingdom of Great Britain."},{"question":"Which TWO things can you do to look after the environment?","choices":["Recycle your waste and never turn your lights off in your house","Drive your car as much as possible and never turn the lights off in your house","Recycle your waste and walk and use public transport to get around","Drive your car as much as possible and recycle your waste"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"It is important to recycle as much of your waste as you can, so the amount of rubbish being put into landfill is reduced. Walking and using public transport to get around when you can is also a good way to protect the environment."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["In Elizabeth I\u2019s time, English settlers began to colonise Australia.","In Elizabeth I\u2019s time, English settlers began to colonise the eastern coast of America."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"In Elizabeth I\u2019s time, English settlers first began to colonise the eastern coast of America."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["All Acts of Parliament are made in the monarch's name.","All Acts of Parliament are made in the Prime Minister's name."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The monarch is the head of state of the UK. All Acts of Parliament are made in the monarch's name."},{"question":"Which of the following is a Crown dependency?","choices":["England","Northern Ireland","Channel Islands","Scotland"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Channel Islands are closely linked with the UK but are not part of it. These islands have their own governments and are called \u2018Crown dependencies\u2019."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Local elections are normally held in May.","Local elections are normally held in March."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"For most local authorities, local elections for councillors are held in May every year."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIf you are a Commonwealth citizen living in the UK, you can vote in all public elections.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Adult citizens of the UK, and citizens of the Commonwealth and Ireland who are resident in the UK, can vote in all public elections."},{"question":"Which TWO are examples of civil law?","choices":["Housing law and employment law","Drugs law and racial crime law","Employment law and drugs law","Housing law and racial crime law"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Civil law is used to settle disputes between individuals or groups. Examples of civil law include housing law, employment law, consumer rights and laws related to the recovery of debt."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThere are many variations in language in the different parts of the UK.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"There are many variations in language in the different parts of the UK. The English language has many accents and dialects. In Wales, many people speak Welsh. In Scotland, Gaelic is spoken in some parts of the Highlands and Islands, and in Northern Ireland some people speak Irish Gaelic."},{"question":"Which of these is the name of a novel by Jane Austen?","choices":["Sense and Sensibility","Far from the Madding Crowd","Oliver Twist","Our Man in Havana"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Jane Austen was an English novelist. Her books include Pride and Prejudice and Sense and Sensibility. Her novels are concerned with marriage and family relationships. Many have been made into television programmes or films."},{"question":"Which of the following is the capital city of Wales?","choices":["Swansea","Cardiff","Edinburgh","Belfast"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The capital city of Wales is Cardiff."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following do you have to pay tax on?","choices":["Income from property, savings and dividends, and small amounts of money given to you as a gift","Income from property, savings and dividends, and shopping vouchers given to you by family or friends","Profits from self-employment, and income from property, savings and dividends","Profits from self-employment, and shopping vouchers given to you by family or friends"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"People in the UK have to pay tax on their income, which includes profits from self-employment, and income from property, savings and dividends. Money raised from income tax pays for government services such as roads, education, police and the armed forces."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Jane Austen and Charles Dickens were famous novelists.","Jane Austen and Charles Dickens were famous painters."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Jane Austen and Charles Dickens were famous novelists. Jane Austen's books include Pride and Prejudice, and Sense and Sensibility. Charles Dickens's novels include Oliver Twist and Great Expectations."},{"question":"After slavery was abolished in the British Empire, more than 2 million migrants came from which TWO countries to replace the freed slaves?","choices":["India and China","Russia and China","India and Australia","Russia and Australia"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"After 1833, 2 million Indian and Chinese workers were employed to replace the freed slaves."},{"question":"Which TWO courts deal with minor criminal cases in the UK?","choices":["Justice of the Peace Court and Magistrates' Court","Centre Court and Crown Court","Justice of the Peace Court and Crown Court","Crown Court and Magistrates' Court"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In England, Wales and Northern Ireland, most minor criminal cases are dealt with in a Magistrates' Court. In Scotland, minor criminal offences go to a Justice of the Peace Court."},{"question":"Which of the following is a British overseas territory?","choices":["Solomon Islands","Australia","Falkland Islands","Malta"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"There are several British overseas territories in other parts of the world, such as the Falkland Islands."},{"question":"Which TWO commemorations or celebrations are held in November each year?","choices":["Remembrance Day and Bonfire Night","Father's Day and Valentine's Day","Valentine's Day and Remembrance Day","Valentine's Day and Bonfire Night"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Bonfire Night, 5 November, is an occasion when people in Great\r\nBritain set off fireworks at home or in special displays. Remembrance Day, 11 November, commemorates those who died fighting for the UK and its allies."},{"question":"Henry VII established the House of Tudor. What colour rose became the Tudor emblem?","choices":["White","Red and white","Red","Pink"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Tudor rose was a red rose with a white rose inside it, showing the alliance between the Houses of York and Lancaster, which had previously fought against each other."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Richard Arkwright developed new farming methods in the UK.","Richard Arkwright ran efficient and profitable factories."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Richard Arkwright is remembered for the efficient and profitable way that he ran his factories."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nSir Isaac Newton was a famous musician from the 18th century.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Sir Isaac Newton was a famous scientist who showed how gravity applied to the whole universe."},{"question":"At which festival are mince pies traditionally eaten?","choices":["Easter","Diwali","Christmas","Vaisakhi"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Christmas is celebrated in a traditional way. People usually spend the day at home and eat a special meal, which often includes roast turkey, Christmas pudding and mince pies."},{"question":"Which TWO rights are offered by the UK to citizens and permanent residents?","choices":["Free groceries for everyone and a right to a fair trial","Long lunch breaks on Friday and a right to a fair trial","Freedom of speech and a right to a fair trial","Freedom of speech and free groceries for everyone"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"There are responsibilities and freedoms which are shared by all those living in the UK. These include freedom of speech and a right to a fair trial."},{"question":"St George is the patron saint of which country?","choices":["England","Scotland","Wales","Northern Ireland"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"St George is the patron saint of England, and is celebrated on 23rd of April each year."},{"question":"Which of the following do you need to do in order to get a full driving licence?","choices":["Pass a driving test","Buy a car or van","Pay income tax","Find a full-time job"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"To get a full UK driving licence, you must pass a driving test, which tests both your knowledge and your practical skills."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["County Courts deal with criminal cases.","County Courts deal with civil disputes."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"County Courts deal with a wide range of civil disputes. These include people trying to get back money that is owed to them, cases involving personal injury, family matters, breaches of contract, and divorce."},{"question":"Which season of orchestral classical music has been organised by the BBC since 1927?","choices":["The Eisteddfod","Aldeburgh Festival","The Proms","Glastonbury"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Proms is an eight-week summer season of orchestral classical music that takes place in various venues, including the Royal Albert Hall in London. It has been organised by the British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC) since 1927."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Hadrian's Wall was built by the Roman Emperor Hadrian.","Hadrian's Wall was built by the Picts (ancestors of the Scottish people) to keep out the Romans."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Emperor Hadrian built a wall in the north of England (Hadrian's Wall) to keep out the Picts (ancestors of the Scottish people)."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe Scottish Parliament can pass laws for Scotland on all matters.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Scottish Parliament can pass laws for Scotland on all matters that are not specifically reserved to the UK Parliament."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\n'In 1921 a peace treaty was signed which led to Ireland becoming two countries.'","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In 1921 a peace treaty was signed and in 1922 Ireland became two countries. The six counties in the north which were mainly Protestant remained part of the UK under the name Northern Ireland. The rest of Ireland became the Irish Free State. It had its own government and became a republic in 1949."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["By 1400 the preferred language of the English court was French.","By 1400 the preferred language of the English court was English."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"By 1400 the preferred language of the royal court was English, which was also the language of official documents."},{"question":"After the Bill of Rights was passed in 1689, which TWO main political groups emerged?","choices":["Labour and Tories","Whigs and Tories","Whigs and Nationalists","Nationalists and Tories"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"From 1689 onwards there were two main groups in Parliament, known as the Whigs and the Tories."},{"question":"Which TWO were 20th-century British discoveries or inventions?","choices":["Mobile phones and walkmans","Cashpoints (ATMs) and walkmans","Cloning a mammal and cashpoints (ATMs)","Cloning a mammal and mobile phones"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In 1996 Sir Ian Wilmut and Keith Campbell led a team which was the first to succeed in cloning a mammal. In the 1960s James Goodfellow invented the cashpoint (ATM)."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Elizabeth I was not successful in balancing her wishes and views against those of the House of Lords and the House of Commons","Elizabeth I was successful in balancing her wishes and views against those of the House of Lords and the House of Commons"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Elizabeth was successful in balancing her wishes and views against those of the House of Lords and the House of Commons. Her successor James I and his son Charles I were less politically skilled."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["By the middle of the 17th century the last Welsh rebellions had been defeated.","By the middle of the 15th century the last Welsh rebellions had been defeated."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The last Welsh rebellions were defeated by the middle of the 15th century."},{"question":"How many people serve on a jury in Scotland?","choices":["8","11","15","20"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In Scotland a jury has 15 members. In England, Wales and Northern Ireland a jury has 12 members."},{"question":"Which TWO are associated with Sir Francis Drake?","choices":["Defeating the Spanish Armada and early flight","Defeating the Spanish Armada and sailing around the world","Early flight and the Titanic","The Titanic and sailing around the world"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Sir Francis Drake was one of the commanders in the defeat of the Spanish Armada. His ship, the Golden Hind, was one\r\nof the first to sail right around (\u2018circumnavigate\u2019) the world."},{"question":"What is the name of the UK currency?","choices":["Dollar","Euro","Pound sterling","Yen"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The currency in the UK is the pound sterling (symbol \u00a3). There are 100 pence in a pound."},{"question":"Which country did Germany invade in 1939 that led to the UK declaring war on Germany?","choices":["Austria","Finland","Poland","France"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"When Adolf Hitler invaded Poland in 1939, Britain and France, declared war on Germany in order to stop his aggression."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Battle of Agincourt is commemorated in the Bayeux Tapestry.","The Battle of Hastings is commemorated in the Bayeux Tapestry."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Bayeux Tapestry commemorates the victory of William, Duke of Normandy at the Battle of Hastings in 1066."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are recent British film actors that have won Oscars?","choices":["Tilda Swinton and Jayne Torvill","Colin Firth and Robert Louis Stevenson","Jayne Torvill and Colin Firth","Tilda Swinton and Colin Firth"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Recent British actors to have won Oscars include Colin Firth, Sir Antony Hopkins, Dame Judi Dench, Kate Winslet and Tilda Swinton."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe Home Secretary is the government minister responsible for managing relationships with foreign countries.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Home Secretary is the government minister responsible for crime, policing and immigration. The Foreign Secretary is the government minister responsible for managing relationships with foreign countries."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nA husband who forces his wife to have sex can be charged with rape.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Any man who forces a woman to have sex, including a woman's husband, can be charged with rape."},{"question":"What were TWO important aspects of the Reform Act of 1832?","choices":["It abolished rotten boroughs and gave women the vote","It decreased the power of the monarch and it gave women the vote","It greatly increased the number of people who could vote and abolished rotten boroughs","It increased the power of the monarch and it gave women the vote"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Reform Act of 1832 greatly increased the number of people with the right to vote. The Act also abolished the old pocket and rotten\r\nboroughs  (parliamentary seats where there were few voters) and more parliamentary seats were given to the towns and cities."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nMembers of the armed forces cannot stand for public office.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Most citizens of the UK, Ireland or the Commonwealth aged 18 or over can stand for public office. There are some exceptions, including members of the armed forces."},{"question":"Who has to pay National Insurance Contributions?","choices":["Almost everybody in the UK who is in paid work","Only people who work full-time","Only those aged 50 and below","Only single people with no dependants"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Almost everybody in the UK who is in paid work, including self-employed people, must pay National Insurance Contributions. The money raised is used to pay for state benefits and services such as the state retirement pension and the National Health Service (NHS)."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Mousetrap is a play that has been running in London's West End since 1952.","The Mousetrap is an environmental policy aiming to prevent mice from destroying crops."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Mousetrap, a murder-mystery play by Dame Agatha Christie, has been running in the West End since 1952."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["When buying a car, you must pay an annual vehicle tax.","When buying a car, you do not need to pay vehicle tax if the previous owner has already paid it."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"When you buy a car, you must pay an annual vehicle tax, which cannot be passed on when a vehicle changes hands."},{"question":"What important event happened in England in 1066?","choices":["The Romans left England","The building of the Offa Dyke","The Norman Conquest","The Battle of Bannockburn"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In 1066, William, the Duke of Normandy (in what is now northern France), defeated Harold, the Saxon king of England, at the Battle of Hastings. The Norman Conquest was the last successful foreign invasion of England and led to many changes in government and social structures in England."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following plants are particularly associated with the UK?","choices":["Shamrock and rose","Cactus and olive tree","Rose and cactus","Shamrock and cactus"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The countries that make up the UK\r\nall have flowers which are particularly associated with them and which are sometimes worn on national saints\u2019 days. In England, the flower is the rose; in Northern Ireland it is the shamrock."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIn 1805, at the Battle of Trafalgar, Admiral Nelson defeated the German fleet.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Britain\u2019s navy fought against combined French and Spanish fleets, winning the Battle of Trafalgar in 1805. Admiral Nelson was in charge of the British fleet at Trafalgar and was killed in the battle."},{"question":"What celebration takes place each year on 14 February?","choices":["Valentine's Day","Bonfire Night","Halloween","Hogmanay"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Valentine\u2019s Day, on 14 February, is when lovers exchange cards and\r\ngifts. Sometimes people send anonymous cards to someone they\r\nsecretly admire."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Sir Steve Redgrave is a famous rower who won gold medals in five consecutive Olympic Games.","Sir Steve Redgrave is a famous film actor who has won several BAFTAs."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Sir Steve Redgrave won gold medals in rowing in five consecutive Olympic Games and is one of Britain\u2019s greatest\r\nOlympians."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nUK citizens must practise a Christian religion.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"False - everyone has the legal right to choose their religion, or to choose not to practise a religion."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nA traditional food in Wales is Ulster fry.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Ulster fry is a traditional food in Northern Ireland. It is a fried meal with bacon, eggs, sausage, black pudding, white pudding, tomatoes, mushrooms, soda bread and potato bread."},{"question":"Why is Sir Edwin Lutyens famous?","choices":["He won a gold medal at the London 2012 Olympic Games.","He was the first UK Prime Minister.","He invented the World Wide Web.","He was a 20th-century architect."],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Sir Edwin Lutyens was a famous 20th-century architect who designed the Cenotaph in Whitehall."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nFlorence Nightingale is famous for her work on education in the 19th century.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Florence Nightingale (1820\u20131910) worked in military hospitals, treating soldiers\r\nwho were fighting in the Crimean War. She and her fellow nurses improved the conditions in the hospital and reduced the mortality rate. She is often regarded as the founder of modern nursing."},{"question":"What happens when a Member of Parliament (MP) dies or resigns?","choices":["The post remains vacant until the next General Election.","Their party chooses someone to fill the post until the next General Election.","A by-election is held to replace the MP.","A neighbouring MP looks after the constituency."],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"If an MP dies or resigns, there will be a fresh election, called a by-election, in his or her constituency."},{"question":"During which part of the year are pantomime productions staged in theatres?","choices":["Easter","Summer","Christmas","Valentine's Day"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Many theatres produce a pantomime at Christmas time. They are light-hearted plays with music and comedy, enjoyed by family audiences."},{"question":"How often are Members of Parliament (MPs) elected?","choices":["At least every three years","Every six months","Every year","At least every five years"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"MPs are elected at a General Election, which is held at least every five years."},{"question":"Which of the following is dealt with under civil law?","choices":["Debt","Violent crime","Burglary","Disorderly behaviour"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Debt is covered by civil law. People might be taken to court if they owe money to someone."},{"question":"Which TWO religions celebrate Diwali?","choices":["Hindus and Christians","Hindus and Sikhs","Christians and Sikhs","Buddhists and Christians"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Diwali is celebrated by Hindus and Sikhs. It celebrates the victory of good over evil and the gaining of knowledge."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are famous British film directors?","choices":["Sir Alfred Hitchcock and Evelyn Waugh","Evelyn Waugh and Thomas Gainsborough","Sir Alfred Hitchcock and Sir Ridley Scott","Evelyn Waugh and Sir Ridley Scott"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Sir Alfred Hitchcock and Sir Ridley Scott are British film directors who have had great success in the UK and internationally."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nDuring the Victorian period the British Empire became the largest empire the world has ever seen.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"During the Victorian period, the British Empire grew to cover all\r\nof India, Australia and large parts of Africa. It became the largest\r\nempire the world has ever seen, with an estimated population of\r\nmore than 400 million people"},{"question":"Which TWO points about slavery are correct?","choices":["William Wilberforce was a leading abolitionist and the Royal Navy refused to stop ships carrying slaves","Quakers set up the first anti-slavery groups and the Royal Navy refused to stop ships carrying slaves","Slavery survived in the British Empire until the early 20th century and the Royal Navy refused to stop ships carrying slaves","William Wilberforce was a leading abolitionist and Quakers set up the first anti-slavery groups"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The first formal anti-slavery groups were set up by the Quakers in\r\nthe late 1700s, and they petitioned Parliament to ban the practice.\r\nWilliam Wilberforce, an evangelical Christian and a member of Parliament, also played an important part in changing the law, and in 1833 the Emancipation Act abolished slavery throughout the British Empire."},{"question":"What is the minimum age at which you can legally buy alcohol in the UK?","choices":["","","",""],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"It is a criminal offence to sell alcohol to anyone who is under 18 or to buy alcohol for people who are under the age of 18. (There is one exception: people aged 16 or over can drink alcohol with a meal in a hotel or restaurant)."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The 'Swinging Sixties' was a period of religious change.","The 'Swinging Sixties' was a period of social change."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The 1960s was a period of significant social change. It was known as \u2018the Swinging Sixties\u2019. There was growth in British fashion, cinema and popular music."},{"question":"Which event occurs each year on the third Sunday in June?","choices":["Halloween","Father's Day","Boxing Day","Remembrance Day"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Father\u2019s Day is the third Sunday in June. Children send cards or buy\r\ngifts for their fathers."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe Scottish Parliament sits in Edinburgh.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Scottish Parliament was formed in 1999. It sits in Edinburgh, the\r\ncapital city of Scotland."},{"question":"What must police officers do?","choices":["Be rude and abusive","Obey the law","Make a false statement","Commit racial discrimination"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Police officers must obey the law. They must not be rude or abusive, make a false statement, misuse their authority, or commit racial discrimination."},{"question":"How are local councils funded?","choices":["Through money raised from local fundraising events","Through donations from local people","By central government and local taxes","From local businesses"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Towns, cities and rural areas in the UK are governed by democratically elected councils, often called 'local authorities'. These are funded by money from central government and by local taxes."},{"question":"What is the minimum age you can drive a car or motor cycle in the UK?","choices":["17","21","18","25"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In the UK, you must be at least 17 years old to drive a car or motor cycle and you must have a driving licence to drive on public roads."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are British overseas territories?","choices":["Canada and Malaysia","Falklands Islands and St Helena","Falkland Islands and Malaysia","Canada and St Helena"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"There are several British overseas territories in other parts of the world, such as St Helena and the Falkland Islands. They are linked to the UK but are not a part of it."},{"question":"Which sport can be traced back to 15th-century Scotland?","choices":["Surfing","Formula 1","Golf","Motorbike racing"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The modern game of golf can be traced back to 15th century\r\nScotland."},{"question":"To which TWO international associations or agreements does the UK belong?","choices":["The North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) and the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA)","The North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) and the Commonwealth","The Commonwealth and the Arab League","The Commonwealth and the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA)"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The UK belongs to many International bodies including NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Organization) and the Commonwealth."},{"question":"The term 'D-Day' refers to which event in British history?","choices":["The Battle of Trafalgar","Landing of allied troops in Normandy","Dropping of the atom bomb on Japan","End of the war in Europe in 1945"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"On 6 June 1944 (often referred to as 'D-Day'), allied forces landed in Normandy. Following victory on the beaches of Normandy, the allied forces pressed on through France\r\nand eventually into Germany."},{"question":"If your car is more than three years old, how often will it need a Ministry of Transport (MOT) test?","choices":["Every three years","Every six months","Every 10 years","Every year"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"If your car is over three years old, you must take it for a Ministry of Transport (MOT) test every year. It is an offence not to have an MOT certificate if your vehicle is more than three years old."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe 'Swinging Sixties' is a reference to the 1860s.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The decade of the 1960s was a period of significant social change.\r\nIt was known as \u2018the Swinging Sixties\u2019. There was growth in British\r\nfashion, cinema and popular music."},{"question":"Is the following statement TRUE or FALSE?\r\nBritish values and principles are based on history and traditions.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"British society is founded on fundamental values and principles, which are based on history and traditions and are protected by law, customs and expectations."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nPantomimes are plays based on fairy stories.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Pantomime plays are a British tradition. Many theatres produce a pantomime at Christmas time. They are based on fairy stories and are light-hearted plays with music and comedy."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe main political parties actively look for members of the public to help at elections and contribute to their costs.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The main political parties actively look for members of the public\r\nto join their debates, contribute to their costs, and help at elections\r\nfor Parliament or for local government. They have branches in most constituencies and hold policy-making conferences every year."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Black Death caused the death of one third of people in Ireland","The Black Death caused the death of one third of people in England, Scotland and Wales"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"In 1348, a disease, probably a form of plague, came to Britain.\r\nThis was known as the Black Death. One third of the population of\r\nEngland died and a similar proportion in Scotland and Wales."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nWales united with England during the reign of Henry VIII.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"During the reign of Henry VIII, Wales became formally united with England by the Act for the Government of Wales"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The public can listen to debates in the House of Commons.","No member of the public is allowed to attend debates in the House of Commons."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The public can listen to debates from public galleries in both the House of Commons and the House of Lords."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Rugby was introduced to ancient Britain by Viking invaders.","Rugby originated in England in the early 19th century."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Rugby originated in England in the early 19th century and is a very popular sport in the UK today."},{"question":"Which cross on the Union Flag represents the patron saint of Ireland?","choices":["The diagonal white cross","The diagonal red cross","The upright red cross","None of these"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The cross of St Patrick, patron saint of Ireland, is a diagonal red cross on a white background."},{"question":"Which of these was Isambard Kingdom Brunel famous for building?","choices":["Motor cars","Aeroplanes","Bridges","Skyscrapers"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Isambard Kingdom Brunel was a famous Victorian engineer who built railway lines, bridges, tunnels and ships."},{"question":"Which TWO records tell us about England during the time of William the Conqueror?","choices":["The Domesday Book and the Bayeux Tapestry","The Diary of Samuel Pepys and the Bayeux Tapestry","The Domesday Book and the Magna Carta","The Diary of Samuel Pepys and the Magna Carta"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Domesday Book is a record of towns and villages in England. The Bayeux Tapestry tells the story of the Norman Conquest."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe Isle of Man is a Crown dependency.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Like the Channel Islands, the Isle of Man is a Crown dependency with its own government."},{"question":"What was the name given to supporters of King Charles I during the Civil War?","choices":["Luddites","Roundheads","Cavaliers","Levellers"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The king's supporters during the Civil War were called Cavaliers. Those who supported Parliament were called Roundheads."},{"question":"Which of the following UK landmarks is in Northern Ireland?","choices":["Big Ben","Snowdonia","The Giant's Causeway","The Eden Project"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Located on the north-east coast of Northern Ireland, the Giant\u2019s\r\nCauseway is a land formation of columns made from volcanic\r\nlava."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["You have to be aged 18 or over to buy a National Lottery ticket.","You have to be aged 16 or over to buy a National Lottery ticket."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"People under the age of 18 are not allowed to participate in the National Lottery."},{"question":"The Bill of Rights of 1689 limited whose powers?","choices":["The king's","Parliament's","Judges'","The Church's"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Bill of Rights of 1689 confirmed the rights of Parliament and the limits of the king\u2019s power."},{"question":"Which TWO fought in wars against Napoleon?","choices":["Winston Churchill and the Duke of Wellington","Margaret Thatcher and the Duke of Wellington","Margaret Thatcher and Admiral Nelson","Admiral Nelson and the Duke of Wellington"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Admiral Nelson commanded the British fleet at the Battle of Trafalgar in 1805. He died during the battle. The Duke of Wellington defeated Napoleon at the Battle of Waterloo in 1815."},{"question":"How often does Prime Minister's Questions occur when Parliament is sitting?","choices":["Every day","Twice a week","Once a week","Once a month"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Prime Minister's Questions takes place every week while Parliament is sitting."},{"question":"St Andrew is the patron saint of which country?","choices":["England","Scotland","Wales","Northern Ireland"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"St Andrew is the patron saint of Scotland, and is celebrated on 30 November each year."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nPressure and lobby groups try to influence government policy.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Pressure and lobby groups are organisations which try to influence government policy. They play an important role in politics."},{"question":"How can you reduce your carbon footprint?","choices":["Shop locally for products","Buy duty-free products when you're abroad","Do all your shopping online","Drive to the supermarket"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"A good way to support your local community is to shop for products\r\nlocally where you can. This will help businesses and farmers in your area and in Britain. It will also reduce your carbon footprint, because the products you buy will not have had to travel as far."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Every household with a device that can be used to watch TV must have a television licence.","People who watch TV only on their computers do not need to pay for a television licence."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Everyone in the UK with a TV, computer or other medium which can be used for watching TV must have a television licence. One licence covers all of the equipment in one home, except when people rent different rooms in a shared house and each has a separate tenancy agreement \u2013 those people must each buy a separate licence."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are part of the UK government?","choices":["The cabinet and the civil service","The civil service and FIFA","The National Trust and FIFA","The cabinet and the National Trust"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"There are several different parts of government in the UK, including the cabinet and the civil service."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The UK offers its citizens and permanent residents freedom of speech.","The UK does not allow citizens or permanent residents to voice opinions publicly."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The UK offers citizens and permanent residents various freedoms and rights, including freedom of speech."},{"question":"How is the Speaker of the House of Commons chosen?","choices":["By the monarch","Through a public election","In a secret ballot","By the Prime Minister"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Speaker is chosen by other Members of Parliament (MPs) in a secret ballot. The Speaker keeps order during political debates to make sure the rules are followed."},{"question":"Who was given the title of Lord Protector in the 17th century?","choices":["King Charles II","Samuel Pepys","Oliver Cromwell","Isaac Newton"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Oliver Cromwell was given the title of Lord Protector and ruled until his death in 1658."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nSir Mo Farah and Dame Jessica Ennis-Hill are well-known athletes who won\r\ngold medals at the 2012 London Olympics.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Sir Mo Farah won gold medals in the 5,000 and 10,000 metres, and Dame Jessica Ennis-Hill won a gold medal in the heptathlon."},{"question":"Which TWO political parties formed the coalition government in 2010?","choices":["Labour and Chartists","Chartists and Liberal Democrats","Conservatives and Liberal Democrats","Conservatives and Labour"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In May 2010, the Conservative and Liberal Democrat parties formed a coalition and the leader of the Conservative Party, David Cameron, became Prime Minister."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC) is financed by income tax.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The money from TV licences is used to pay for the British\r\nBroadcasting Corporation (BBC). Everyone in the UK with a TV, computer or other medium which can be used for watching TV must have a television licence."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe 40 days before Easter are known as Lent.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Lent is a time when Christians take time to reflect and prepare for Easter. Traditionally, people would fast during this period and today many people will give something up, like a favourite food."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The capital city of Scotland is Edinburgh.","The capital city of Scotland is Glasgow."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The capital city of Scotland is Edinburgh."},{"question":"When is a by-election for a parliamentary seat held?","choices":["Half-way through a parliamentary term","Every two years","When a Member of Parliament (MP) dies or resigns","When the Prime Minister decides to call one"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"If an MP dies or resigns, there will be a fresh election, called a by-election, in his or her constituency."},{"question":"What sort of cases do Crown Courts and Sheriff Courts deal with?","choices":["Small claims procedures","Youth cases","Minor criminal cases","Serious offences"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"In England, Wales and Northern Ireland, serious offences are tried in front of a judge and jury in a Crown Court. In Scotland, serious cases are heard in a Sheriff Court with either a sheriff or a sheriff with a jury."},{"question":"Bobby Moore is famous for his achievements in which sport?","choices":["Football","Rugby union","Horse racing","Motor racing"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Bobby Moore captained the England football team that won the World Cup in 1966."},{"question":"How old do you have to be to go into a betting shop in the UK?","choices":["21","18","25","30"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"In the UK, people often enjoy a gamble on sports or other events. You have to be over 18 to go into betting shops or gambling clubs."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nMost people live in the countryside in the UK.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Most people in the UK live in towns and cities, but much of Britain is still countryside."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Shakespeare wrote 'To be or not to be'.","Shakespeare wrote 'We will fight on the beaches'."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"'To be or not to be' is a quotation from Hamlet, written by William Shakespeare."},{"question":"What is a fundamental principle of British life?","choices":["Relaxed work ethic","Democracy","Extremism","Disrespect for the law"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"British society is founded on fundamental values and principles which all those living in the UK should respect and support. One of these principles is democracy."},{"question":"Which TWO actions can a judge take if a public body is not respecting someone's legal rights?","choices":["Order the body to pay compensation and close down the public body","Place the body's members in prison and close down the public body","Order the body to change its practices and order the body to pay compensation","Place the body's members in prison and order the body to change its practices"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"If judges find that a public body is not respecting someone's legal rights, they can order that body to change its practices and/or pay compensation."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are UK landmarks?","choices":["Edinburgh Castle and the London Eye","The Eisteddfodd and the National Trust","The National Trust and the London Eye","The National Trust and Edinburgh Castle"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Edinburgh Castle is a dominant feature of the skyline in Edinburgh, Scotland. The London Eye is situated on the southern bank of the River Thames. Both are UK landmarks."},{"question":"Which is the UK's most popular sport?","choices":["Cricket","Golf","Rugby","Football"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Football is the UK's most popular sport. It has a long history in the UK, and the English Premier League attracts a huge international audience."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["It is free to visit the Houses of Parliament to listen to debates.","It costs \u00a315 per person to visit the Houses of Parliament to listen to debates."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The public can listen to debates from public galleries in both the House of Commons and the\r\nHouse of Lords. Entrance is free. You can write to your local MP in advance to ask for tickets or you can queue on the day at the public entrance."},{"question":"Where is the UK parliament based?","choices":["Holyrood","Senedd","Stormont","Westminster"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The UK is governed by the parliament sitting in Westminster."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Several British writers have won the Nobel Prize in Literature.","No British writer has won the Nobel Prize in Literature."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Several British writers, including the novelist Sir William Golding, the poet Seamus Heaney, and the playwright Harold Pinter, have won the Nobel Prize in Literature."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nBritain and Germany developed Concorde, a supersonic passenger aircraft.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"False - Britain and France developed Concorde, the supersonic passenger aircraft. It first flew in 1969 and began carrying passengers in 1976. Concorde was retired from service in 2003."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThere is no place in British society for extremism or intolerance.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"British society is founded on fundamental values and principles which all those living in the UK respect and support. There is no place for extremism or intolerance."},{"question":"In which country was the composer George Frederick Handel born?","choices":["Iceland","Russia","Japan","Germany"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"George Frederick Handel was born in Germany in 1685. He spent many years in the UK and became a British citizen in 1727."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\n'Great Britain' refers only to England, Scotland and Wales.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Great Britain' refers only to England, Scotland and Wales, not to Northern Ireland."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nAn example of a civil law case is when you have purchased a faulty item and made a legal complaint.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Civil law is used to settle disputes between individuals or groups."},{"question":"Which of the following is a responsibility you will have as a citizen or permanent resident of the UK?","choices":["To keep your dog on a lead at all times","To avoid shopping on a Sunday","To look after yourself and your family","To grow your own vegetables"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"There are responsibilities and freedoms which are shared by all those living in the UK. These include looking after yourself and your family."},{"question":"Which TWO foods are associated with England?","choices":["Ulster fry and roast beef","Haggis and roast beef","Roast beef, and fish and chips","Haggis and Ulster fry"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Roast beef is served with potatoes, vegetables, Yorkshire puddings and other accompaniments. Fish and chips are also popular in England."},{"question":"Which TWO developments are associated with the 'Swinging Sixties'?","choices":["Reform of abortion law and introduction of decimal currency","Reform of children's rights law and introduction of decimal currency","Reform of children's rights law and reform of divorce law","Reform of abortion law and reform of divorce law"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"During the 1960s (a period known as the 'Swinging Sixties'), a number of social changes took place. Many social laws were liberalised, for example, in regard to abortion and divorce in England, Wales and Scotland."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Gilbert and Sullivan were a comedy double act.","Gilbert and Sullivan wrote many comic operas."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"In the 19th century, Gilbert and Sullivan wrote comic operas, often\r\nmaking fun of popular culture and politics. These operas include\r\nHMS Pinafore, The Pirates of Penzance and The Mikado."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following were introduced in the early 20th century?","choices":["Child Benefit payments and free school meals","The National Health Service (NHS) and Child Benefit payments","The National Health Service (NHS) and old-age pensions","Old-age pensions and free school meals"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The early 20th century was a time of social progress. Old-age pensions and free school meals were just a few of the important measures introduced."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland have parliaments or assemblies of their own.","Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland do not have parliaments or assemblies of their own."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland have parliaments or assemblies of their own, with devolved powers in defined areas."},{"question":"What type of church is the Church of Scotland?","choices":["Quaker","Roman Catholic","Presbyterian","Methodist"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"In Scotland, the national Church is the Church of Scotland, which is\r\na Presbyterian Church."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Women in Britain make up about a quarter of the workforce.","Women in Britain make up about half of the workforce."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Women in Britain make up about half of the workforce. Employment opportunities for women are much greater than they were in the past."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nWales, Scotland and Northern Ireland each have devolved administrations which give them total control over all policies and laws.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Some powers have been devolved from central government to give people in Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland more control over matters that directly affect them. Some policy and laws remain under central UK government control."},{"question":"St David is the patron saint of which country of the UK?","choices":["England","Scotland","Wales","Northern Ireland"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"St David is the patron saint of Wales, and St David's Day is celebrated on 1 March each year."},{"question":"What is a bank holiday?","choices":["A public holiday when banks and many other businesses close for the day","A holiday just for people working in banks","A week off for everyone in the UK","An extra holiday entitlement for working longer hours than usual"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"There are public holidays each year, called bank holidays, when banks and many other businesses close for the day."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIn the UK you are expected to treat others with fairness.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"There are responsibilities and freedoms which are shared by all those living in the UK.  These include treating others with fairness."},{"question":"Which of the following is a British overseas territory?","choices":["Northern Ireland","Falkland Islands","France","USA"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"There are several British overseas territories in other parts of the world, such as the Falkland Islands."},{"question":"Which of these events changed the powers of the king in 1215?","choices":["The Domesday Book","The Magna Carta","The Reform Act","The Black Death"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"In 1215, King John was forced by his noblemen to agree to a number of demands. The result was a charter of rights called the Magna Carta (which means the Great Charter). The Magna Carta established the idea that even the king was subject to the law. It protected the rights of the nobility and restricted the king\u2019s power to collect taxes or to make or change laws."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The National Trust is a charity that works to preserve important buildings in the UK.","The National Trust is a government-run organisation that provides funding for charities."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The National Trust in England, Wales and Northern Ireland, and the National Trust for Scotland, work to preserve important buildings, coastline and countryside."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nYou can support your local community by becoming a school governor.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"School governors are people from the local community who wish to make a positive contribution to children\u2019s education."},{"question":"What is the youngest age at which you can be asked to serve on a jury?","choices":["22","18","16","30"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Anyone who is on the electoral register and is aged 18\u201370 (18\u201375 in England and Wales) can be asked to serve on a jury."},{"question":"Where do the Laurence Olivier awards take place?","choices":["London","Cardiff","Edinburgh","Belfast"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Laurence Olivier Awards take place annually at different venues\r\nin London. There are a variety of categories, including best director,\r\nbest actor and best actress."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Highland Clearances took place in Scotland.","The Highland Clearances took place in Ireland."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Highland Clearances took place in Scotland. Many Scottish landlords destroyed individual small farms (known as \u2018crofts\u2019) to make space for large flocks of sheep and cattle."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Members of the House of Lords are not elected by the people.","Members of the House of Lords are voted in by members of the House of Commons."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Members of the House of Lords are not elected by the people and do not represent a constituency."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The UK is a member of NATO.","The UK has never been a member of NATO."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The UK is a member of NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Organization). NATO is a group of European and North American countries that have agreed to help each other if they come under attack. It also aims to maintain peace between all of its members."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Police and Crime Commissioners (PCCs) are appointed through a public election.","Police and Crime Commissioners (PCCs) are appointed by the local council."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The public in England and Wales elect Police and Crime Commissioners (PCCs). The first elections for PCCs were held in November 2012."},{"question":"With which sport do you associate Lewis Hamilton, Jenson Button and Damon Hill?","choices":["Football","Athletics","Skiing","Formula 1"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Lewis Hamilton, Jenson Button and Damon Hill are all British Grand Prix drivers who have won the Formula 1 World Championship."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["There are a few Members of Parliament who do not represent any of the main political parties.","All Members of Parliament have to belong to a political party."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"There are a few Members of Parliament (MPs) who do not represent any of the main political parties. They are called 'independents'."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The capital cities of the nations of the UK are London, Swansea, Glasgow and Dublin.","The capital cities of the nations of the UK are London, Cardiff, Edinburgh and Belfast."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The capital cities of the nations of the UK are: London (England), Cardiff (Wales), Edinburgh (Scotland) and Belfast (Northern Ireland)."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The UK is made up of England, Scotland, Wales and Ireland.","The UK is made up of England, Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The UK is made up of England, Scotland, Wales and Northern\r\nIreland. The rest of Ireland is an independent country."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe Channel Islands are a part of the UK.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Channel Islands are closely linked with the UK but are not part of it. They have their own governments and are called \u2018Crown dependencies\u2019."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["After the Bill of Rights was declared in 1689, two political groups emerged, the Whigs and the Tories.","After the Bill of Rights was declared in 1689, two political groups emerged, the Labour Party and the Greens."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"After the Bill of Rights was declared in 1689,  there were two main groups in Parliament, known\r\nas the Whigs and the Tories. (The modern Conservative Party is\r\nstill sometimes referred to as the Tories.)"},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nWilliam Blake, Lord Byron and Robert Browning were all famous golfers.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"William Blake, Lord Byron and Robert Browning were all poets."},{"question":"Which of these groups can take part in the National Citizen Service programme?","choices":["All children up to the age of 17","Pensioners","16- and 17-year-olds","18- to 30-year-olds"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The National Citizen Service programme gives 16- and 17-year-olds the opportunity to enjoy outdoor activities, develop their skills and take part in a community project."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nNorthern Ireland and Scotland have their own banknotes.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Northern Ireland and Scotland have their own banknotes, which are valid everywhere in the UK."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Lancelot 'Capability' Brown and Gertrude Jekyll were famous garden designers.","Lancelot 'Capability' Brown and Gertrude Jekyll were famous characters in a Sherlock Holmes story."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In the 18th century, Lancelot \u2018Capability\u2019 Brown designed the grounds around country houses so that the landscape appeared to be natural, with grass, trees and lakes. Later, Gertrude Jekyll often worked with Sir Edwin Lutyens to design colourful gardens around the houses he designed."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The first person to use the title Prime Minister was Sir Robert Walpole.","The first person to use the title Prime Minister was Sir Christopher Wren."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Sir Robert Walpole was the first person to be called Prime Minister. He was Prime Minister from 1721 until 1742."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are part of the UK?","choices":["St Helena and Scotland","Wales and Scotland","Channel Islands and Wales","Wales and St Helena"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The UK is made up of England, Scotland, Wales and Northern\r\nIreland."},{"question":"The term 'suffragettes' is associated with which group of people?","choices":["Men","Women","Children","Migrants"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"In the late 19th and early\r\n20th centuries, an increasing number of women campaigned and\r\ndemonstrated for greater rights and, in particular, the right to vote.\r\nThey formed the women\u2019s suffrage movement and became known\r\nas \u2018suffragettes\u2019."},{"question":"In 1999, what happened to hereditary peers in the House of Lords?","choices":["Their numbers were greatly increased.","Their salaries were stopped.","Women were allowed to inherit their titles.","They lost their automatic right to attend the House of Lords."],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Since 1999, hereditary peers have lost the automatic right to attend the House of Lords. They now elect a few of their number to represent them in the House of Lords."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Cricket matches can last up to five days.","Cricket matches can last up to two weeks."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Some cricket games can last for up to five days and still result in a draw."},{"question":"Which TWO are Protestant Christian groups in the UK?","choices":["Methodists and Roman Catholics","Baptists and Hindus","Baptists and Methodists","Roman Catholics and Sikhs"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Baptists and Methodists are Protestant Christian groups. Other Protestant groups in the UK include the Church of England, the Church of Scotland, Presbyterians and Quakers."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following were major welfare changes introduced from 1945 to 1950?","choices":["The National Health Service (NHS) and a national system of benefits"," The State retirement pension and employment exchanges","The National Health Service (NHS) and employment exchanges","Employment exchanges and free school meals"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Labour government that was elected in 1945 established the National Health Service (NHS) and a national system of benefits."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Winston Churchill was the British Prime Minister during the First World War.","Winston Churchill was the British Prime Minister during the Second World War."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Winston Churchill was the British Prime Minister from 1940  to 1945, during the Second World War."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are part of the UK?","choices":["Ireland and Canada","Canada and England","England and Northern Ireland","Ireland and England"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The UK is made up of England, Scotland, Wales and Northern\r\nIreland. The rest of Ireland is an independent country."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nOn the 1st of April, people in the UK play jokes on each other until midday.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"April Fool\u2019s Day, 1 April, is a day when people play jokes on each\r\nother until midday. The television and newspapers often have stories that are April Fool jokes."},{"question":"What is the title of the National Anthem of the UK?","choices":["Long Live the King","God Save the King","Long Live the Monarch","Almighty is the King"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The National Anthem of the UK is 'God Save the King'. It is played at important national occasions and at events attended by the King or the Royal Family."},{"question":"Which of the following is a fundamental principle of British life?","choices":["Extremism","Individual liberty","Intolerance","Inequality"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Individual liberty is a fundamental principle of British life. There is no place in British society for extremism or intolerance."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Wars of the Roses were between the Houses of Lancaster and York.","The Wars of the Roses were between the Houses of Windsor and Tudor."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In 1455, a civil war was begun to decide who should be king of\r\nEngland. It was fought between the supporters of two families:\r\nthe House of Lancaster and the House of York. This war was called\r\nthe Wars of the Roses, because the symbol of Lancaster was a red\r\nrose and the symbol of York was a white rose."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe daffodil is the national flower of Wales.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The daffodil is the national flower of Wales, and is worn on St David's Day."},{"question":"Which parts of the United Kingdom have devolved governments?","choices":["England and Wales","Wales, England and Northern Ireland","Only Northern Ireland","Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Some powers have been devolved from central government to give people in Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland more control over matters that directly affect them."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nIn the UK you are expected to respect the rights of others to have their own opinions.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"There are responsibilities and freedoms which are shared by all those living in the UK. These include respecting the rights of others, including their right to their own opinions."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe House of Lords always acts as the government wishes.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The House of Lords is normally more independent of the government than the House of Commons."},{"question":"Which of the following groups of adults is NOT eligible to vote in all UK elections?","choices":["Citizens of the USA","Adult citizens of the UK","Citizens of the Commonwealth who are resident in the UK","Citizens of Ireland who are resident in the UK"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Adult citizens of the UK, and citizens of the Commonwealth and Ireland who are resident in the UK, can vote in all public elections."},{"question":"Which TWO are famous gardens in the UK?","choices":["Sissinghurst and Snowdonia","London Eye and Sissinghurst","London Eye and Snowdonia","Sissinghurst and Bodnant Garden"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Sissinghurst is in England and Bodnant Garden is in Wales."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nOn average, boys in the UK leave school with better qualifications than girls.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"On average, girls leave school with better qualifications than boys. Also, more women than men study at university."},{"question":"What type of government was formed after the General Election of 2010?","choices":["National","All-party","One-party","Coalition"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The 2010 coalition was formed by the Conservative and Liberal Democrat parties."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Carrying a weapon is an example of a criminal offence.","Being in debt is an example of a criminal offence."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Carrying a weapon is one example of a criminal offence. Crimes are usually investigated by the police and punished by the courts."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nWhen Queen Anne died in 1714, parliament chose a German to be the next king of England.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Queen Anne had no surviving children, so Parliament chose a German, George I, to be the next king, because he was Anne\u2019s nearest\r\nProtestant relative."},{"question":"Which TWO are famous British composers?","choices":["Henry Purcell and Ralph Vaughan Williams","Johann Sebastian Bach and Henry Purcell","Claude Debussy and Henry Purcell","Claude Debussy and Johann Sebastian Bach"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Henry Purcell wrote church music, opera and other pieces, and developed a British style distinct from that elsewhere in Europe. Ralph Vaughan Williams wrote music for orchestras and choirs. He was strongly influenced by traditional English folk music."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Sir Andy Murray is the first British man to sail around the world.","Sir Andy Murray is the first British man to win a singles tennis title in a Grand Slam tournament since 1936."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Sir Andy Murray is a Scottish tennis player and the first British man to win a singles tennis title in a Grand Slam tournament since 1936."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE OR FALSE? \r\nMembers of the public are allowed to attend Youth Court hearings.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Members of the public are not allowed in Youth Courts, and the name or photographs of the accused young person cannot be published in newspapers or used by the media."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The small claims procedure is an informal way of helping people to settle minor disputes.","The small claims procedure helps people to make small home insurance claims."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The small claims procedure is an informal way of helping people to settle minor disputes without spending a lot of time and money using a lawyer."},{"question":"How old do you need to be in order to stand for public office?","choices":["16","18","20","21"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Most citizens of the UK, Ireland or the Commonwealth aged 18 or over can stand for public office."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nDuring the 18th century, new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed. This period is often called 'the Enlightenment'.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"During the 18th century, new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed. This period is often called \u2018the Enlightenment\u2019. One of the most important principles of the Enlightenment was that\r\neveryone should have the right to their own political and religious beliefs and that the state should not try to dictate to them."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following were famous Victorians?","choices":["Isambard Kingdom Brunel and Margaret Thatcher","Isambard Kingdom Brunel and Florence Nightingale","Margaret Thatcher and Dylan Thomas","Margaret Thatcher and Florence Nightingale"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Isambard Kingdom Brunel (1806\u20131859) was a famous engineer, and Florence Nightingale (1820\u20131910) established a training school for nurses, the first of its kind."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following were English Civil War battles?","choices":["Marston Moor and Hastings","Waterloo and Marston Moor","Hastings and Naseby","Marston Moor and Naseby"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The Battles of Marston Moor and Naseby were English Civil War battles."},{"question":"What is a fundamental principle of British life?","choices":["The rule of law","The rule of the upper classes","The rule of the monarch","The rule of your local Member of Parliament (MP)"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The rule of law is a fundamental principle of British life. British society is founded on fundamental values and principles which all those living in the UK should respect and support."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nDundee and Aberdeen are cities in Northern Ireland.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Dundee and Aberdeen are cities in Scotland."},{"question":"Which cross on the Union Flag represents the patron saint of Scotland?","choices":["The diagonal white cross","The diagonal red cross","The upright red cross","None of these"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The cross of St Andrew, patron saint of Scotland, is a diagonal white cross on a blue ground."},{"question":"What are TWO benefits of volunteering?","choices":["You can earn additional money and you are given a courtesy car as transport","You can meet new people and you are given a courtesy car as transport","You can meet new people and you help to make your community a better place","You can earn additional money and you can meet new people"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"Volunteering is working for good causes without payment. There are many benefits to volunteering, including meeting new people and helping make your community a better place."},{"question":"Hadrian's Wall was built to keep out whom?","choices":["The Irish","The Welsh","The Picts","The Vikings"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Roman Emperor Hadrian built the wall in the north of England to keep out the Picts (ancestors of the Scottish people)."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Volunteering is a good way to earn additional money.","Volunteering is a way of helping others without receiving payment."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Volunteering is working for good causes without payment. There are many activities you can do as a volunteer, such as working with the homeless and helping improve the environment."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nJohn Constable (1776\u20131837) founded the modern police force in England.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"John Constable was a landscape painter most famous for his works of Dedham Vale on the Suffolk\u2013Essex border in the east of England."},{"question":"Which TWO developments were features of the Industrial Revolution?","choices":["Machinery and steam power","Changes in the law and steam power","Machinery and medical advances","Medical advances and changes in the law"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Britain was the first country to industrialise on a large scale. This happened because of the development of machinery and the use of steam power."},{"question":"Which TWO services are funded by National Insurance Contributions?","choices":["State retirement pension and National Health Service (NHS)","Supermarket home deliveries and National Health Service (NHS)","Local taxi services and state retirement pension","State retirement pension and supermarket home deliveries"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Almost everybody in the UK who is in paid work, including self-employed people, must pay National Insurance Contributions. The money raised is used to pay for state benefits and services such as the state retirement pension and the National Health Service (NHS)."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["George and Robert Stephenson were famous pioneers of railway engines.","George and Robert Stephenson were famous pioneers of agricultural changes."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"George and Robert Stephenson were famous pioneers of railway engines."},{"question":"Which part of the UK is associated with Robert Burns (1759\u20131796)?","choices":["England","Scotland","Wales","Northern Ireland"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Robert Burns is associated with Scotland. He was a poet. One of his best-known works is the song Auld Lang Syne."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Donated blood is used by hospitals to help people with a wide range of injuries and illnesses","Donated blood is not used by hospitals to help people with a wide range of injuries and illnesses"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Donated blood is used by hospitals to help people with a wide range\r\nof injuries and illnesses. Giving blood only takes about an hour to do."},{"question":"To apply for UK citizenship or permanent residency, which TWO things do you need?","choices":["An ability to speak and read English, and a good knowledge of life in the UK","A UK bank account and an ability to speak and read English","A UK bank account and a good understanding of life in the UK","An ability to speak and read English, and a driving licence"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"To apply to become a permanent resident or a naturalised citizen of\r\nthe UK, you must be able to speak and read English and have a good understanding of life in the UK."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["In 1588 the English defeated the Spanish Armada.","In 1588 the English defeated German bomber planes."],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"In 1588, the English defeated the Spanish Armada (a large fleet of ships), which had been sent by Spain to conquer England and restore Catholicism."},{"question":"Which of the following is the capital city of the UK?","choices":["Westminster","Birmingham","Windsor","London"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"The capital city of the UK is London, which is in England."},{"question":"Which of the following is a responsibility you will have as a citizen or permanent resident of the UK?","choices":["Using your car as much as possible","Visiting your local pub regularly","Keeping an allotment","Looking after the area in which you live and the environment"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"There are responsibilities and freedoms which are shared by all those living in the UK.  These include looking after the area in which you live and the environment."},{"question":"What was the Reformation?","choices":["A reduction in the power of the nobles","A movement against the authority of the Pope","A part of the Wars of the Roses","A bill of rights"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Reformation occurred across Europe. It was a movement against the authority of the Pope and the ideas and practices of the Roman Catholic Church."},{"question":"Which collection of poems was written by Geoffrey Chaucer?","choices":["The Westbury Tales","The Ambridge Tales","The London Tales","The Canterbury Tales"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Geoffrey Chaucer wrote a series\r\nof poems about a group of people going to Canterbury\r\non a pilgrimage. This collection of poems is called The Canterbury\r\nTales."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following types of case are held in County Courts?","choices":["Divorce and murder","Murder and minor criminal offences","Minor criminal offences and breaches of contract","Divorce and breaches of contract"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"County Courts deal with a wide range of civil disputes, including divorce and other family matters, and breaches of contract."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following are major outdoor music festivals?","choices":["Hogmanay and Glastonbury","Royal Ascot and the Isle of Wight Festival","Royal Ascot and Hogmanay","Isle of Wight Festival and Glastonbury"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"Festival season takes place across the UK every summer, with major events in various locations. Famous festivals include Glastonbury, the Isle of Wight Festival and Creamfields."},{"question":"For which TWO reasons is Henry VIII remembered?","choices":["Married six times and fought in the Battle of Agincourt","Married six times and broke away from the Church of Rome","Introduced the game of croquet and married six times","Introduced the game of croquet and fought in the Battle of Agincourt"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Henry VIII is remembered for breaking away from the Catholic Church of Rome and marrying six times."},{"question":"Which countries make up 'Great Britain'?","choices":["Just England","England, Scotland and Wales","England and Scotland","England, Scotland and Northern Ireland"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"'Great Britain' refers only to England, Scotland and Wales, not to Northern Ireland. The official name of the country is the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland."},{"question":"Which TWO of the following were important 20th-century inventors?","choices":["Tim Berners-Lee and Isambard Kingdom Brunel","Alan Turing and Tim Berners-Lee","George Stephenson and Isambard Kingdom Brunel","Alan Turing and George Stephenson"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"Alan Turing (1912\u20131954) invented a theoretical mathematical device called a Turing Machine that led to the development of the modern-day computer. Tim Berners-Lee (1955\u2013) invented the World Wide Web."},{"question":"When a Member of Parliament (MP) dies or resigns, what is the election called that is held to replace them?","choices":["Re-selection","Selection","Hustings","By-election"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"If a Member of Parliament (MP) dies or resigns, there will be a fresh election, called a by-election, in his or her constituency."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["The Reform Act of 1832 reduced the number of people who had the right to vote.","The Reform Act of 1832 increased the number of people who had the right to vote."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The Reform Act of 1832 greatly increased the number of people with the right to vote. There was a permanent shift of political\r\npower from the countryside to the towns but voting was still based\r\non ownership of property. This meant that members of the working class were still unable to vote."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Decisions on government policies are made by the monarch.","Decisions on government policies are made by the Prime Minister and cabinet."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The monarch has regular meetings with the Prime Minister, and can advise, warn and encourage, but the decisions on government policies are made by the Prime Minister and cabinet."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe Lake District is England's largest national park.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"The Lake District is England\u2019s largest national park. It covers 912 square miles (2,362 square kilometres)."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nA General Election occurs every eight years.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"A General Election is held at least every five years."},{"question":"When you arrive at a polling station, the staff will ask for which of the following:","choices":["Photocopy of your passport.","Name, address and photo ID.","Life in the UK test certificate.","National Insurance number."],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"People vote in elections at places called polling stations, or polling places in Scotland. When you arrive at the polling station, the staff will ask for your name, address and photo ID. You can check that you have the right photo ID at www.gov.uk/how-to-vote/photo-id-youll-need. You will then get your ballot paper, which you take to a polling booth to fill in privately."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nAll citizens and permanent residents of the UK can choose which laws they follow.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"There are responsibilities and freedoms which are shared by all those living in the UK.  These include respecting and obeying the law."},{"question":"Which TWO famous London buildings are built in the 19th-century 'gothic' style?","choices":["The Houses of Parliament and Buckingham Palace","St Paul's Cathedral and St Pancras Station","St Paul's Cathedral and Buckingham Palace","The Houses of Parliament and St Pancras Station"],"correct_answer":3,"explanation":"In the 19th century, the medieval 'gothic' style became popular again. The Houses of Parliament and St Pancras Station were built at this time."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nGetting to know your neighbours can help you to become part of the community.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Getting to know your neighbours can help you to become part of the community and make friends. Your neighbours are also a good source of help."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE OR FALSE?\r\nThe British constitution is contained in a single written document.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The British constitution is not written down in any single document, and therefore it is described as 'unwritten'."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThe shamrock is the national flower of Scotland.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":1,"explanation":"The shamrock is the national flower of Northern Ireland, and the thistle is the national flower of Scotland."},{"question":"The Union Flag consists of three crosses. One is the cross of St George. Who do the other TWO crosses represent?","choices":["St David and St Piran","St David and St Andrew","St Patrick and St Andrew","St Patrick and St Piran"],"correct_answer":2,"explanation":"The Union Flag consists of the crosses of Saints George, Andrew and Patrick."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nUK population growth has been faster in more recent years.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"UK population growth has been faster in more recent years. Migration into the UK and longer life expectancy have played a part in this."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nPeople can see the Crown Jewels at the Tower of London.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"True - people can see the Crown Jewels at The Tower of London."},{"question":"Is the statement below TRUE or FALSE?\r\nThere is a dragon on the official flag of Wales.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct_answer":0,"explanation":"Wales has its own flag, which shows a dragon. The Welsh dragon does not appear on the Union Flag because, when the first Union Flag was created in 1606 from the flags of Scotland and England, the Principality of Wales was already united with England."}]}